<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 <lb/>| https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>Inflammatory bowel disease <lb/>biomarkers revealed by the human <lb/>gut microbiome network <lb/>Mirko Hu 1 , Guido Caldarelli 2,3,4,5* &amp; Tommaso Gili 6 <lb/>Inflammatory bowel diseases (IBDs) are complex medical conditions in which the gut microbiota is <lb/>attacked by the immune system of genetically predisposed subjects when exposed to yet unclear <lb/>environmental factors. The complexity of this class of diseases makes them suitable to be represented <lb/>and studied with network science. In this paper, the metagenomic data of control, Crohn&apos;s disease, <lb/>and ulcerative colitis subjects&apos; gut microbiota were investigated by representing this data as <lb/>correlation networks and co-expression networks. We obtained correlation networks by calculating <lb/>Pearson&apos;s correlation between gene expression across subjects. A percolation-based procedure <lb/>was used to threshold and binarize the adjacency matrices. In contrast, co-expression networks <lb/>involved the construction of the bipartite subjects-genes networks and the monopartite genes-genes <lb/>projection after binarization of the biadjacency matrix. Centrality measures and community detection <lb/>were used on the so-built networks to mine data complexity and highlight possible biomarkers of <lb/>the diseases. The main results were about the modules of Bacteroides, which were connected in the <lb/>control subjects&apos; correlation network, Faecalibacterium prausnitzii, where co-enzyme A became <lb/>central in IBD correlation networks and Escherichia coli, whose module has different patterns of <lb/>integration within the whole network in the different diagnoses. <lb/></front>

			<body>Microbes are ubiquitous. They can be found everywhere, from radioactive waste to the human gastrointestinal <lb/>tract. In and on the human body, they have evolved to co-exist with their host, and it is estimated that the num-<lb/>ber of microbes hosted by the human body is of the same order of magnitude as the number of human cells 1 . In <lb/>particular, the 10 14 commensal microbes in the intestinal tract form the human gut microbiota, which has evolved <lb/>to live in symbiosis with its host 2 . It is widely accepted that this symbiosis begins from birth, and the microbial <lb/>communities stabilize with age until the formation of an adult microbiota 3 . Its genetic content (called the micro-<lb/>biome) characterizes everyone, also raising concerns about identity and privacy issues, specifically when the study <lb/>and the manipulation of the microbiota are considered 4 . Since the 1840s, when the concept of gut microbiota <lb/>first appeared, the topic has been studied for two centuries 5 , and, at the moment, it is known that the gut micro-<lb/>biota has a fundamental role in shaping the gut barriers 6 , training the host immune system and regulating the <lb/>metabolism 7 . When the compositional and metabolic equilibrium of the commensal microbes living in the gut <lb/>is disrupted, different types of diseases arise, such as metabolic disorders or central nervous system disorders 8 . <lb/>Historically, traditional medicine attempted to re-establish this equilibrium through remedies intervening in <lb/>the digestive system, such as fasting, diets, and the assumption of spring waters or laxatives. A recent procedure <lb/>that was introduced to tackle the Clostridioides difficile infection is the faecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) 9 <lb/>which consists in repopulating the intestinal tract of an ill subject with the microbiota of a healthy donor. <lb/>Inflammatory bowel diseases (IBDs), which comprise Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) and ulcerative colitis (UC), are <lb/>an essential class of diseases that arise from dysbiosis and are being treated with FMT. Typical symptoms of this <lb/>class of diseases are chronic diarrhoea, abdominal pain, rectal bleeding, weight loss, and fatigue 10 . Although CD <lb/>and UC are both characterized by the inflammation of the intestinal tract, there are several differences between <lb/>the two diagnoses that span from the environmental factors that cause them, e.g., smoking or diet, to the clini-<lb/>cal and endoscopic findings in the two diagnoses 11 . Overall, IBDs are becoming widespread in modern society <lb/>because of lifestyle changes, socioeconomic developments, and environmental causes 12 . Until now, it has been <lb/>known that IBD is an exaggerated immune response to the gut microbiota of genetically predisposed subjects <lb/></body>

			<front>OPEN <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Medicine and Surgery, University of Parma, 43121 Parma, Italy. 2 Department of Molecular Science <lb/>and Nanosystems, Ca&apos; Foscari University of Venice, 30123 Venice, Italy. 3 Institute of Complex Systems, National <lb/>Research Council (ISC-CNR), 00185, Rome, Italy. 4 Fondazione per il Futuro delle Città, FFC, 50133 Firenze, <lb/>Italy. 5 European Centre for Living Technology, (ECLT), 30123 Venice, Italy. 6 Networks Unit, IMT School for <lb/>Advanced Studies Lucca, 55100 Lucca, Italy. * email: guido.caldarelli@unive.it <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>under the influence of the external environment. This complex interplay between genetics, the microbiota, the <lb/>immune system and the environment makes it particularly hard to understand this class of diseases. Kirsner 13 <lb/>offered a complete historical review of the IBD until the 1980s, by quoting Hippocrates, who described diarrhoea <lb/>as a symptom of an infectious (or non-infectious) disease to a description of the hypothetical pathogenesis of <lb/>IBD, which the microbiota was not considered, though. A more recent projection predicted the evolution of the <lb/>disease between 2015 and 2025 and updated the possible origins of IBD, including the action of antibiotics on <lb/>the gut microbiota in Western society 14 . Xavier et al. 15 summarized the findings of the origins of IBD, mentioning <lb/>the complexity of the disease. Another historical review focuses on the genetics of the IBD 16 identified NOD2 as <lb/>the first CD susceptible gene and then described the evolution of the IBD genetics with the coming of the mod-<lb/>ern genome-wide association study. One of the first and most comprehensive works describing the interaction <lb/>of all the aforementioned factors can be found in Ref. 17 . The systems biology approach to the study of IBD was <lb/>presented by Fiocchi et al. 18 , which proposed the creation of an IBD interactome, a complex system connecting <lb/>all the potential agents interacting among them that derived from the combination of different omics 19 . <lb/>Our work starts from here and attempts to provide tools and methods from network science useful to build <lb/>and study the IBD interactome with a systems biology approach by commencing from the metagenomic data of <lb/>the gut microbiome. This approach is typical of network medicine, a novel discipline that mixes network science <lb/>with systems biology to tackle the challenges offered by the progress of personalized medicine 20 , which opposes <lb/>the current effective yet drastic procedures like the FMT. Network science is the discipline used to analyse com-<lb/>plex systems. It could be suited to understand a complex disease like IBD in which a complex system like the gut <lb/>microbiota plays a fundamental role. Complexity in the intestinal microbial communities arises at different scales; <lb/>from the macroscopic point of view, we have the ecological interactions 21,22 that describe the relationships among <lb/>the species in the gut microbiota; among these, we have three different main types of interactions 23 ; positive <lb/>interactions (cooperation, commensalism, cross-feeding), negative interactions (competition, ammensalism), <lb/>and asymmetric interactions (exploitation, predation, parasitism). Going towards a microscopic scale, we can <lb/>find the gene networks, often represented by gene co-expression networks 24 and metabolic networks built by <lb/>connecting the substances, known as metabolites, reacting in the same metabolic processes 25 . <lb/>The application of network science for the study of the complexity of the gut microbiome is recent, and one <lb/>of the first research was in the case of C. difficile infection 26 . The microbiome in this work was represented as a <lb/>boolean network derived from binarized temporal data of the abundance of specific bacteria species in the gut. <lb/>Although the study captured the dynamics of the bacterial species, e.g., negative, positive or neutral interac-<lb/>tion, it did not take into account the genetic expression of the microbiome (metagenome), which could better <lb/>explain the complex interplay between the bacterial species. Our study, by contrast, gives a static screenshot of <lb/>the microbial interactions through metagenomics. A more recent study 27 analysed the co-abundance network <lb/>built with SparCC 28 ; the need for this tool is due to the necessity of sparsifying the network that would have <lb/>too many correlated nodes because of normalization and a p-value threshold too high 29 . Based on a topologi-<lb/>cal property of the biological networks, the work by Vernocchi et al. 24 portrays a weighted gene co-expression <lb/>network analysis by building a network from metagenomic data and removing the weaker edges based on the <lb/>assumption that the final network would be scale-free. In our work, we used thresholding methods that rely on <lb/>the network topology, such as the percolation threshold or the p-value for the projected edges, similar to the later <lb/>research. These methods should overcome the aforementioned problems. Furthermore, the emergence of specific <lb/>network properties (community detection, betweenness centrality) can be used as possible IBD biomarkers. In a <lb/>complex system, such as the gut microbiota, it is hard to observe changes in single biomarkers. Diseases emerge <lb/>from malfunctioning in the collective behaviour of the nodes. Therefore, community detection and between-<lb/>ness centralities are important properties to be analysed. The former describes how the pathways are grouped <lb/>in the complex system and the latter represents the pillar pathways among all the interactions that sustain the <lb/>collective functioning of the network. <lb/>Results <lb/>In the next paragraphs, each pathway is called with a code name composed of the pathway code and the related <lb/>species (e.g., &quot;PATHWAYCODE|SPECIES&quot;) for the sake of brevity and clarity, it is possible to consult the table <lb/>mapping the correspondences between the codes and the complete pathway (Table S1 of Supplementary Mate-<lb/>rial). The properties of the main pathways can be found in the same table, the BioCyc 30 and the MetaCyc 31 col-<lb/>lections. The small set of reads that are mapped to proteins and are not associated with pangenomics are labelled <lb/>as &quot;unclassified&quot; 32 . <lb/>Bacteroides and Faecalibacterium prausnitzii <lb/>The correlation networks for each diagnosis were obtained by isolating the samples of each diagnosis and then <lb/>calculating the Pearson correlation of the samples to obtain a weighted network that was made binary through a <lb/>percolation threshold of each diagnosis network ( th DIAGNOSIS ). Each correlation network was built by collecting <lb/>the pathways from subjects diagnosed with Crohn&apos;s disease (CD), ulcerative colitis (UC) or healthy non-IBD (NI). <lb/>The pathways were divided into prevalent (if present in more than 75% of the samples), common (if present in <lb/>50% to 75% of the samples) and uncommon (if present in 25% to 50% of the samples). We refer to the Methods <lb/>section for a more detailed description of the methods. In the prevalent pathways, the number of edges in the NI <lb/>correlation network was 3356 ( th NI = 0.453 ), in CD correlation network was 2905 ( th CD = 0.357 ), and in the <lb/>UC correlation network was 3160 ( th UC = 0.364 ). The results showed that the NI metagenome was more con-<lb/>nected for prevalent pathways and the percolation threshold was higher compared to the percolation thresholds <lb/>in the CD and the UC correlation networks, translating into more strongly correlated nodes in the NI correlation <lb/>network. The community detection algorithm, which reveals the groups (called modules or communities) of <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>nodes in the network based on their topological similarities, aims to maximise the modularity. The maximised <lb/>modularity is an important descriptor of the network structure; the lower the modularity, the lower the total <lb/>number of modules. We obtained that the lowest modularity (0.538) can be found in the NI correlation network, <lb/>meaning that it was not possible to separate some of the modules and there would be interconnections between <lb/>them, the CD and the UC correlation networks resulted in a modularity of 0.583 and 0.622, respectively. <lb/>As we can see in Fig. 1, the pathways in the NI correlation network were divided into three large modules, <lb/>one module was isolated, by contrast, the other two modules were communicating strictly through several <lb/>nodes. The isolated module was composed of Phocaeicola vulgatus and Bacteroides uniformis pathways, this <lb/>meant that in control subjects the two species co-variated and were interdependent through specific pathways <lb/>(on the frontiers of the species modules, it was possible to find nodes PWY-6387|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS, <lb/>PWY-6151|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS, PEPTIDOGLYCANSYN-PWY|BACTEIROIDES_UNIFORMIS, <lb/>PWY-5667|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS on the B. uniformis side and nodes PANTO-PWY|PHOCAEICOLA_ <lb/>VULGATUS, PWY-6700|PHOCAEICOLA_VULGATUS, PWY-7220|PHOCAEICOLA_VULGATUS, PWY-<lb/>7222|PHOCAEICOLA_VULGATUS on the P. vulgatus side). The light purple module, on the other hand, <lb/>contained Faecalibacterium prausnitzii, whereas the remaining large module contained the Bacteroides ovatus <lb/>pathways, Eubacterium rectale pathways, and the unclassified species pathways. The nodes with the highest <lb/>betweenness centrality (Table 1), the importance given by the number of shortest paths crossing the node, among <lb/>the unclassified pathways in the two connected modules were connected through: <lb/>1. node PWY-6527|UNCLASSIFIED; <lb/>2. node GLYCOGENSYNTH-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED; <lb/>3. node PWY66-422|UNCLASSIFIED; <lb/>4. node PWY-6317|UNCLASSIFIED. <lb/>Whereas, the nodes with the highest betweenness centrality among the F. prausnitzii pathway module that was <lb/>connected to the unclassified pathway module were: <lb/>1. node PWY-5659|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII; <lb/>2. node PWY-6277|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII; <lb/>3. node PWY-6121|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII; <lb/>4. node PWY-6122|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII. <lb/>To notice that pathway of node PWY-5659|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII correlated with only 4 E. <lb/>rectale pathways. <lb/>In the CD correlation network, there were fewer connections, and the network was divided into 6 mod-<lb/>ules. Each module corresponded to the species groups of pathways. The smallest module was composed of E. <lb/>rectale pathways. The largest (light purple) module comprising F. prausnitzii was connected to the unclassi-<lb/>fied (green) module using node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED similar to the UC correlation network. Moreo-<lb/>ver, an additional bridge connecting node was node SER-GLYSYN-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUS-<lb/>NITZII, which was linked to nodes PWY-6527|UNCLASSIFIED and ILEUSYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED, to <lb/>mention two high betweenness centrality nodes among the unclassified pathways. High betweenness central-<lb/>ity nodes DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED and PWY-5659|BACTEROIDES_OVATUS connected <lb/>unclassified species module with B. ovatus module, node PWY-6124|BACTEROIDES_OVATUS, in turn, was <lb/>connected to node PWY-7219|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS linking B. ovatus module to the B. uniformis <lb/>module. Finally, similarly to the NI correlation network, P. vulgatus and B. uniformis were connected though <lb/>(nodes PWY-3841|PHOCAEICOLA_VULGATUS, PWY-7221|PHOCAEICOLA_VULGATUS, and PWY-<lb/>7228|PHOCAEICOLA_VULGATUS on the former side and nodes PWY0-845|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS <lb/>Table 1. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the non-IBD (NI) correlation <lb/>network with prevalent pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>821 <lb/>PWY-6527|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.094492 <lb/>466 <lb/>PWY-5659|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.031006 <lb/>610 <lb/>PWY-6122|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.026071 <lb/>724 <lb/>PWY-6277|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.026071 <lb/>177 <lb/>GLYCOGENSYNTH-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.024356 <lb/>579 <lb/>PWY-6121|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.017164 <lb/>1225 <lb/>PWY66-422|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.015345 <lb/>751 <lb/>PWY-6317|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.014598 <lb/>1090 <lb/>PWY-7242|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.010309 <lb/>499 <lb/>PWY-5667|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.007929 <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>and 1CMET2-PWY|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS on the latter side). The pathways with the highest between-<lb/>ness centralities can be found in Table 2. <lb/>The pathways in the UC correlation network were divided into 5 modules. The smallest module (coral red) was <lb/>composed of E. rectale pathways scattered around the network. The dark green nodes mixed with the turquoise <lb/>nodes were B. ovatus pathways mixed with B. uniformis pathways, respectively. The green module comprised of <lb/>unclassified species pathways, whereas, the light purple module comprised of F. prausnitzii pathways. The green <lb/>and the light purple modules were strictly connected similarly to the NI correlation network, the pathways con-<lb/>necting them were the node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED, which was linked to several nodes of both modules and <lb/>node PWY-6121|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, which was linked to nodes PWY-724|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>and THRESYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED. Even E. rectale behaved as a bridge between the two large modules <lb/>through a few connections. Furthermore, there was one node of F. prausnitzii module that was deeply correlated <lb/>with all the P. vulgatus pathways: node DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII. Finally, <lb/>two nodes with high betweenness centrality were node PWY-6737|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII in the <lb/>light purple module and node PWY-6703|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS in the mixed dark green and turquoise <lb/>module (see Table 3). Differently from the NI correlation network, B. uniformis did not correlate P. vulgatus, <lb/>whereas it correlated with B. ovatus. <lb/>In Fig. 2, we have projected the bipartite network, a graph with two distinct sets of nodes (namely samples and <lb/>pathways), onto the nodes of the bacterial pathways and we validate the projection through a null model (with the <lb/>following parameters; significance threshold α = 0.05 and family-wise error rate fwer = none ). Again, we divided <lb/>the pathways according to their presence along with the samples. We considered the case of 75% of the presence <lb/>across the samples for NI subjects. We found 1715 edges for 153 nodes and the community detection resulted in 6 <lb/>large communities; namely, the unclassified species community, the F. prausnitzii community, the E. rectale com-<lb/>munity, the B. uniformis community, the B. ovatus community and P. vulgatus community. All the communities <lb/>identified were isolated, the node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED was connected to the unclassified module through <lb/>the nodes PWY-6609|UNCLASSIFIED, PWY-3001|UNCLASSIFIED, and THRESYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED. <lb/>Also, nodes PWY-5100|UNCLASSIFIED and PANTO-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED were separated from the rest of <lb/>the unclassified module. Considering F. prausnitzii module, nodes PWY0-1586|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUS-<lb/>NITZII, PWY-6305|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, and PWY-5659|-FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUS-<lb/>NITZII were disconnected from the rest of the module. In Table 4, the pathways with the highest centrality <lb/>belonged to unclassified and F. prausnitzii. This can explained by the fact that the two groups of pathways are <lb/>merged in a unique module. <lb/>Table 2. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) <lb/>correlation network with prevalent pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>137 <lb/>DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.419592 <lb/>462 <lb/>PWY-5659|BACTEROIDES_OVATUS <lb/>0.414082 <lb/>632 <lb/>PWY-6124|BACTEROIDES_OVATUS <lb/>0.349599 <lb/>988 <lb/>PWY-7219|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS <lb/>0.342192 <lb/>105 <lb/>COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.258219 <lb/>1261 <lb/>SER-GLYSYN-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.133321 <lb/>204 <lb/>ILEUSYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.116815 <lb/>5 <lb/>1CMET2-PWY|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS <lb/>0.10414 <lb/>1205 <lb/>PWY0-845|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS <lb/>0.073644 <lb/>821 <lb/>PWY-6527|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.051347 <lb/>Table 3. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) <lb/>correlation network with prevalent pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>901 <lb/>PWY-6737|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.319 <lb/>105 <lb/>COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.315 <lb/>873 <lb/>PWY-6703|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS <lb/>0.311 <lb/>133 <lb/>DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.179 <lb/>579 <lb/>PWY-6121|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.110 <lb/>1093 <lb/>PWY-724|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.049 <lb/>1284 <lb/>THRESYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.049 <lb/>101 <lb/>COA-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.037 <lb/>1008 <lb/>PWY-7219|EUBACTERIUM_RECTALE <lb/>0.029 <lb/>1154 <lb/>PWY0-1296|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.022 <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>In the CD case, there were 153 nodes and 1615 edges, the community detection algorithm identified 6 differ-<lb/>ent modules, one for each bacterial species identified in the previous cases. All the communities were isolated <lb/>without nodes connecting them. Differently from the NI case, node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED does not result <lb/>in connection to the rest of the unclassified module. Similarly to the NI case, node PWY-5100|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>was not isolated, whereas node PANTO-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED was well connected to the rest of the unclassi-<lb/>fied module. When F. prausnitzii was considered, we obtained that node PWY0-1586|FAECALIBACTERIUM_ <lb/>PRAUSNITZII was connected to nodes PWY-6317|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII and PWY66-<lb/>422|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, that both were well connected to the F. prausnitzii pathways. <lb/>Also, node PWY-6305|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII differently from the NI projected network is <lb/>connected to two nodes of the bacterium module, namely PWY-6122|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAU-SNITZII <lb/>and PWY-6277|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, which were both pathways involving 5-aminoimidazole <lb/>ribonucleotide. On the other hand, node PWY-5659|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII was connected <lb/>to node PWY-5695|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII and nodes, PWY-6317|FAECALIBACTERIUM_ <lb/>PRAUSNITZII and PWY66-422|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, where the former was involved in <lb/>the biosynthesis of urate and the latter were involved in the degradation of galactose. Similarly to the NI case, in <lb/>Table 5, the pathways with the highest centrality belonged to unclassified and F. prausnitzii. <lb/>In the UC case, we could find 153 nodes and 669 edges. Differently from the previous cases, the commu-<lb/>nity detection algorithm could not isolate modules corresponding to the 6 species of the prevalent pathway <lb/>group. The F. prausnitzii module was split into two modules held together by the nodes GLCMANNANAUT-<lb/>PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII and PWY-5686|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII. Simi-<lb/>larly to the CD projected network, node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED was isolated from the rest of the unclas-<lb/>sified module, whereas node PWY-5100|UNCLASSIFIED was connected to the rest of the module by means <lb/>of nodes BRANCHED-CHAIN-AA-SYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED, ILEUSYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED, PWY-<lb/>5103|UNCLASSIFIED, and CALVIN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED. Differently from the NI projected network and <lb/>similarly to the CD projected network, in the UC projected network, the node PANTO-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>was well connected to the rest of the unclassified module. When the F. prausnitzii module was considered, <lb/>nodes PWY0-1586|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAU-SNITZII, PWY-6305|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUS-<lb/>NITZII, and PWY-5659|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII were isolated from the rest of the module in <lb/>the same fashion as the NI case. Furthermore, the UC projected network by displaying fewer connections <lb/>had more isolated pathways compared to the NI and the CD case. For instance, nodes DTDPRHAMSYN-<lb/>PWY|BACTEROIDES_OVATUS and PWY-7282|BACTEROIDES_OVATUS detached from the B. ovatus <lb/>Table 4. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the non-IBD (NI) projected <lb/>network with prevalent pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>362 <lb/>PWY-3001|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00645 <lb/>413 <lb/>PWY-5097|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00534 <lb/>610 <lb/>PWY-6122|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.00514 <lb/>724 <lb/>PWY-6277|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.00514 <lb/>544 <lb/>PWY-5695|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00430 <lb/>351 <lb/>PWY-2942|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.00421 <lb/>105 <lb/>COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00391 <lb/>1284 <lb/>THRESYN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00313 <lb/>499 <lb/>PWY-5667|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00242 <lb/>1188 <lb/>PWY0-1319|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.00242 <lb/>Table 5. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) projected <lb/>network with prevalent pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>1285 <lb/>TRNA-CHARGING-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0108 <lb/>1225 <lb/>PWY66-422|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0077 <lb/>42 <lb/>ARO-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0066 <lb/>672 <lb/>PWY-6151|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0056 <lb/>525 <lb/>PWY-5686|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0052 <lb/>748 <lb/>PWY-6317|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.0045 <lb/>1222 <lb/>PWY66-422|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.0045 <lb/>865 <lb/>PWY-6700|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0045 <lb/>298 <lb/>PEPTIDOGLYCANSYN-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.0031 <lb/>610 <lb/>PWY-6122|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.0031 <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 6. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the ulcerative colitis (UC) projected <lb/>network with prevalent pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>67 <lb/>CALVIN-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0192 <lb/>158 <lb/>GLCMANNANAUT-PWY|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.0132 <lb/>517 <lb/>PWY-5686|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.0132 <lb/>359 <lb/>PWY-2942|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0113 <lb/>525 <lb/>PWY-5686|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0113 <lb/>865 <lb/>PWY-6700|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0113 <lb/>321 <lb/>PWY-1042|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII <lb/>0.0104 <lb/>821 <lb/>PWY-6527|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0097 <lb/>244 <lb/>NONOXIPENT-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0066 <lb/>121 <lb/>COMPLETE-ARO-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.0036 <lb/>Figure 1. Correlation networks of prevalent metagenomic pathways in (a) NI subjects, (b) CD subjects, (c) <lb/>UC subjects. In (a), nodes in the frontier between P. vulgatus and B. uniformis and in the frontier between F. <lb/>prauznitzii and unclassified modules are highlighted. In (b) and (c), nodes with high betweenness centrality like <lb/>node 105 are highlighted. The legend remarks the species of each node/pathway. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>module, node PWY-7219|EUBACTERIUM_RECTALE detached from the E. rectale module, and several more <lb/>fragments of the module. Similar to the previous two cases, the highest betweenness centrality nodes belonged <lb/>to F. prausnirzii and unclassified groups Table 6. <lb/>Escherichia coli <lb/>As it is possible to observe in Fig. 4, the relatively uncommon pathways were 910 in total. There were 49203 edges <lb/>in NI correlation network ( th NI = 0.474 ), 42617 edges in CD correlation network ( th CD = 0.446 ), 44523 edges in <lb/>UC correlation network ( th UC = 0.465 ). The number of edges was comparable in the three networks. We could <lb/>observe 9 modules in the NI correlation network (modularity 0.623), 9 modules in the CD correlation network <lb/>(modularity 0.644), and 6 modules in the UC correlation network (modularity 0.695). In every network, it was <lb/>possible to identify an approximately isolated ball-shaped module containing E. coli pathways. It was interesting <lb/>to highlight the position of B. fragilis pathways in respect of E. coli pathways in the different diagnoses. In the <lb/>NI correlation network, B. fragilis pathways were connected to the E. coli module through Veillonella parvula <lb/>pathways, by contrast, in the UC correlation network, B. fragilis pathways were incorporated and surrounded <lb/>by the same module containing E. coli pathways, whereas in the CD correlation network, the bacterial path-<lb/>ways of the two species were separated. In the NI correlation network, the module containing E. coli included <lb/>also bacterial pathways of other species, notably Eubacterium siraeum and Ruminococcus gnavus pathways that <lb/>behaved as bridge nodes between E. coli containing the module and the rest of the network. In the CD correlation <lb/>network, this role was assumed by Roseburia intestinalis and V. parvula, whereas, in the UC correlation network, <lb/>we did not observe any pathways behaving as bridge nodes. An additional important module that was also the <lb/>Figure 2. Projected network representation of prevalent metagenomic pathways in (a) NI subjects, (b) CD <lb/>subjects, (c) UC subjects. Networks are obtained through a bipartite projection and the exclusion of an edge <lb/>between two nodes is made through a comparison with a null model. The nodes highlighted describe the <lb/>pathway with the highest betweenness centrality. The legend remarks the species of each node/pathway. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>largest was the one mainly composed of R. torques, Anaerostipes hadrus, Lachnospiraceae bacterium 5 1 63FAA, <lb/>plus other minor species. The pathways belonging to the last two mentioned species were strictly intertwined <lb/>forming the second largest ball-shaped group of nodes. The same ball-shaped group of nodes was present in the <lb/>CD correlation network, by contrast, in the UC correlation network, the two species were in the same module <lb/>and the nodes were not mixed in the ball but they laid separately. The highest betweenness centralities of each <lb/>correlation network can be found respectively in Tables 7, 8, and 9. The NI network contains a variety of central <lb/>pathways from different bacterium species, by contrast, the UC network has several central pathways belonging <lb/>to Enterocloster bolteae. <lb/>In the NI network projection, we obtained a network with 910 nodes and 20078 edges. As it is possible to <lb/>notice in Fig. 5, several modules emerged from the network. The most evident was the E. coli module which <lb/>was one of the modules that composed the E. coli group in the uncommon pathways. This bigger module was <lb/>Table 7. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the non-IBD (NI) correlation <lb/>network with uncommon pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>263 <lb/>PANTO-PWY|RUMINOCOCCUS_GNAVUS <lb/>0.163 <lb/>969 <lb/>PWY-7208|EUBACTERIUM_RECTALE <lb/>0.112 <lb/>1159 <lb/>PWY0-1298|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.043 <lb/>1112 <lb/>PWY-7383|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.039 <lb/>1007 <lb/>PWY-7219|EUBACTERIUM_HALLII <lb/>0.035 <lb/>836 <lb/>PWY-6609|RUMINOCOCCUS_GNAVUS <lb/>0.034 <lb/>819 <lb/>PWY-6527|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII 0.033 <lb/>756 <lb/>PWY-6385|BACTEROIDES_XYLANISOLVENS <lb/>0.032 <lb/>1250 <lb/>RHAMCAT-PWY|ROSEBURIA_INTESTINALIS <lb/>0.031 <lb/>198 <lb/>ILEUSYN-PWY|RUMINOCOCCUS_OBEUM <lb/>0.028 <lb/>Table 8. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) <lb/>correlation network with uncommon pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>156 <lb/>GLCMANNANAUT-PWY|DOREA_LONGICATENA <lb/>0.180 <lb/>500 <lb/>PWY-5676|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.072 <lb/>265 <lb/>PANTO-PWY|BURKHOLDERIALES_BACTERIUM_1_1_47 0.059 <lb/>395 <lb/>PWY-5097|BACTEROIDES_STERCORIS <lb/>0.058 <lb/>247 <lb/>P162-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.053 <lb/>913 <lb/>PWY-6897|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.052 <lb/>1312 <lb/>VALSYN-PWY|DOREA_FORMICIGENERANS <lb/>0.048 <lb/>895 <lb/>PWY-6737|DOREA_LONGICATENA <lb/>0.046 <lb/>670 <lb/>PWY-6151|ROSEBURIA_INTESTINALIS <lb/>0.043 <lb/>1003 <lb/>PWY-7219|DOREA_FORMICIGENERANS <lb/>0.042 <lb/>Table 9. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the ulcerative colitis (UC) <lb/>correlation network with uncommon pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>131 <lb/>DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|ESCHERICHIA_COLI <lb/>0.175 <lb/>571 <lb/>PWY-6121|ENTEROCLOSTER_BOLTEAE <lb/>0.129 <lb/>753 <lb/>PWY-6353|UNCLASSIFIED <lb/>0.097 <lb/>1096 <lb/>PWY-7282|BACTEROIDES_FRAGILIS <lb/>0.097 <lb/>622 <lb/>PWY-6123|BACTEROIDES_FRAGILIS <lb/>0.095 <lb/>178 <lb/>GLYCOL-GLYOXDEG-PWY|ESCHERICHIA_COLI <lb/>0.053 <lb/>599 <lb/>PWY-6122|ENTEROCLOSTER_BOLTEAE <lb/>0.039 <lb/>713 <lb/>PWY-6277|ENTEROCLOSTER_BOLTEAE <lb/>0.039 <lb/>155 <lb/>GLCMANNANAUT-PWY|RUMINOCOCCUS_TORQUES 0.029 <lb/>1143 <lb/>PWY0-1296|ENTEROCLOSTER_BOLTEAE <lb/>0.027 <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>connected to Flavonifractor plautii via 5 nodes on the E. coli side and via 5 nodes on the F. plautii side. On the <lb/>E. coli side: <lb/>1. node FUCCAT-PWY|ESCHERICHIA_COLI; <lb/>2. node PWY-6737|ESCHERICHIA_COLI; <lb/>3. node PWY-6609|ESCHERICHIA_COLI; <lb/>4. node PWY-6703|ESCHERICHIA_COLI; <lb/>5. node PWY-7199|ESCHERICHIA_COLI. <lb/>On the F. plautii side: <lb/>1. node PWY-5188|FLAVONIFRACTOR_PLAUTII; <lb/>2. node PWY-6122|FLAVONIFRACTOR_PLAUTII; <lb/>3. node PWY-6277|FLAVONIFRACTOR_PLAUTII; <lb/>4. node PEPTIDOGLYCANSYN-PWY|FLAVONIFRACTOR_PLAUTII; <lb/>5. node PWY-6121|FLAVONIFRACTOR_PLAUTII. <lb/>Curiously there was also a Enterocloster bolteae pathway well-connected to the E. coli main module (node PWY0-<lb/>1296|ENTERO-CLOSTER_BOLTEAE). The remaining part of the E. coli group was represented by fatty acid <lb/>metabolism pathways (node FAO-PWY|ESCHERICHIA_COLI) or pathways involving mannose biosynthesis, <lb/>which were connected to other species&apos; pathways. Apart from these nodes scattered around the network, the <lb/>species group had two main ball-shaped modules thanks to the well-connected nature of the nodes inside the <lb/>module. Another interesting community was the module formed by the nodes of two different species L. bac-<lb/>terium 5 1 63FAA and A. hadrus. The edges connecting the nodes of the two species were so dense that the two <lb/>groups formed a unique module. Similarly to the NI correlation network, the NI projected network (Table 10) <lb/>has diverse central pathways compared to the CD and UC projected network (Tables 11 and 12) <lb/>In the CD network projection, there were 910 nodes and 26505 edges. One of the immediately visible proper-<lb/>ties of the projected network was the isolated module composed of E. coli pathways. Compared to the NI case, <lb/>there were no connections to the other species nodes. R. torques module was connected to A. hadrus module, <lb/>Table 10. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the non-IBD (NI) projected <lb/>network uncommon pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>27 <lb/>ARGSYNBSUB-PWY|BIFIDOBACTERIUM_LONGUM <lb/>0.153 <lb/>1309 <lb/>VALSYN-PWY|ENTEROCLOSTER_BOLTEAE <lb/>0.148 <lb/>237 <lb/>NONOXIPENT-PWY|ENTEROCLOSTER_BOLTEAE <lb/>0.142 <lb/>1044 <lb/>PWY-7221|BIFIDOBACTERIUM_LONGUM <lb/>0.080 <lb/>878 <lb/>PWY-6703|LACHNOSPIRACEAE_BACTERIUM_5_1_63FAA <lb/>0.070 <lb/>1253 <lb/>SALVADEHYPOX-PWY|RUMINOCOCCUS_TORQUES <lb/>0.042 <lb/>891 <lb/>PWY-6737|CLOSTRIDIUM_LEPTUM <lb/>0.041 <lb/>660 <lb/>PWY-6151|RUMINOCOCCUS_OBEUM <lb/>0.037 <lb/>355 <lb/>PWY-2942|LACHNOSPIRACEAE_BACTERIUM_5_1_63FAA <lb/>0.036 <lb/>55 <lb/>BRANCHED-CHAIN-AA-SYN-PWY|BIFIDOBACTERIUM_LONGUM 0.033 <lb/>Table 11. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) projected <lb/>network with uncommon pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>697 <lb/>PWY-621|ESCHERICHIA_COLI <lb/>0.207 <lb/>81 <lb/>COA-PWY-1|DOREA_LONGICATENA <lb/>0.156 <lb/>680 <lb/>PWY-6163|DOREA_LONGICATENA <lb/>0.098 <lb/>971 <lb/>PWY-7208|PARASUTTERELLA_EXCREMENTIHOMINIS 0.098 <lb/>1265 <lb/>SER-GLYSYN-PWY|RUMINOCOCCUS_BROMII <lb/>0.089 <lb/>625 <lb/>PWY-6123|BACTEROIDES_XYLANISOLVENS <lb/>0.088 <lb/>584 <lb/>PWY-6121|PARASUTTERELLA_EXCREMENTIHOMINIS 0.047 <lb/>615 <lb/>PWY-6122|PARASUTTERELLA_EXCREMENTIHOMINIS 0.047 <lb/>729 <lb/>PWY-6277|PARASUTTERELLA_EXCREMENTIHOMINIS 0.047 <lb/>950 <lb/>PWY-7111|RUMINOCOCCUS_BROMII <lb/>0.047 <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>which in turn was connected to L. bacterium 5 1 63FAA module. 5 nodes of A. hadrus community was connected <lb/>to most of the nodes of the other two species exhibiting high betweenness centrality, they were: <lb/>1. node VALSYN-PWY|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS; <lb/>2. node PWY-5104|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS; <lb/>3. node PWY-5659|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS; <lb/>4. node PWY-6700|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS; <lb/>5. node PWY-6121|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS. <lb/>Similarly to the NI case, node GLCMANNANAUT-PWY|RUMINOCOCCUS_TORQUES was connected only <lb/>to pathways of other species. Another difference with the NI projected network was the edges of R. intestinalis <lb/>which in this case were connected to B. instestinihominis, whereas, in the NI case, they were connected to nodes <lb/>PWY-6151|ROSEBURIA_INULINIVORANS and 1CMET2-PWY|BACTEROIDES_UNIFORMIS. <lb/>The UC network projection had 910 and only 10140 edges. The first striking property of this network was <lb/>that there were much fewer edges compared to the previous two cases. It was not possible to say much about the <lb/>module of E. coli. On the other hand, it was possible to observe that L. bacterium 5 1 63FAA and A. hadrus were <lb/>separated. Furthermore, L. bacterium 5 1 63FAA module was connected to the R. hominis module through several <lb/>nodes. Related to the R. torques group, we had one main module similar to the other cases, two isolated nodes <lb/>(node PWY-7221|RUMINOCOCCUS_TORQUES as the NI case and node PWY-6121|RUMINOCOCCUS_ <lb/>TORQUES) and two nodes connected between them (nodes PWY-6277|RUMINOCOCCUS_TORQUES and <lb/>PWY-6122|RUMINOCOCCUS_TORQUES), but separated from the rest of the pathways. As shown in Fig. 3, <lb/>we found with a two-way ANOVA test a statistically significant difference in the number of edges by network <lb/>type (p &lt; 0.00187 ) for correlation networks, but not diagnosis, the interaction between these terms was not <lb/>significant. On the other hand, edges had not a statistically significant difference by network type nor diagnosis <lb/>for projected networks. <lb/>Table 12. Top 10 pathway nodes with the highest betweenness centrality in the ulcerative colitis (UC) <lb/>projected network with uncommon pathways. <lb/>Node <lb/>Pathway <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>314 <lb/>PWY-1042|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS <lb/>0.0177 <lb/>875 <lb/>PWY-6703|BACTEROIDES_XYLANISOLVENS <lb/>0.0166 <lb/>131 <lb/>DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|ESCHERICHIA_COLI <lb/>0.0109 <lb/>391 <lb/>PWY-5097|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS <lb/>0.0109 <lb/>472 <lb/>PWY-5667|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS <lb/>0.0086 <lb/>1161 <lb/>PWY0-1319|ANAEROSTIPES_HADRUS <lb/>0.0086 <lb/>136 <lb/>DTDPRHAMSYN-PWY|ROSEBURIA_INTESTINALIS 0.0079 <lb/>1108 <lb/>PWY-7357|ROSEBURIA_INTESTINALIS <lb/>0.0079 <lb/>583 <lb/>PWY-6121|ODORIBACTER_SPLACHNICUS <lb/>0.0068 <lb/>320 <lb/>PWY-1042|ESCHERICHIA_COLI <lb/>0.0063 <lb/>Figure 3. The barplots show the number of edges for each diagnosis in correlation networks (a) and projected <lb/>networks (b). <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>In the literature, the reduction of F. prausnitzii has been associated with IBD 33 ; nevertheless, in our results, we <lb/>recognized that instead of a decrease in the quantity of F. prausnitzii pathways expressed, there was a change in <lb/>the wiring in the metagenomic network. In particular, what changed from the NI correlation network and the IBD <lb/>correlation networks were the bridge pathways connecting the module of unclassified pathways and the module <lb/>containing the F. prausnitzii pathways. For instance, in the NI correlation network, the bridge pathway was node <lb/>PWY-6527|UNCLASSIFIED, whereas, in the IBD networks, the bridge pathways between the two modules were <lb/>node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED. The correlation between these bridge nodes and the nodes in the aforemen-<lb/>tioned modules meant that both modules relied on that specific pathway to function correctly. On the one hand, <lb/>the central substance was the tetrasaccharide stachyose which is degraded into UDP-alpha-D-glucose and has <lb/>been recognized as a potential probiotic against enterotoxigenic E. coli 34 ; on the other hand, there was coenzyme <lb/>A, which has a fundamental role in the metabolism and, in particular, is important in the oxidation of fatty acids. <lb/>Several studies linked the alteration of fatty acid production to the IBDs; hence, this change in the centrality of <lb/>the pathway related to this substance could be investigated further to explain the origins of IBDs 34 . The modules <lb/>of Bacteroides in IBD networks corresponded to the single species, whilst in the NI network are gathered in one <lb/>module. This could demonstrate that in IBDs the different Bacteroides species proliferates the gut independently. <lb/>This fact can confirm the meta-analysis by 35 , which showed that lower levels of Bacteroides were associated <lb/>with IBDs. Other pathways differentially wired between NI and IBD networks are those involving the bacterial <lb/>metabolite 5-aminoimidazole ribonucleotide (nodes PWY-6121|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, PWY-<lb/>6122|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII, PWY-6277|FAECALIBACTERIUM_PRAUSNITZII). These nodes <lb/>were behaving as bridges in the NI correlation network; by contrast, in the IBD correlation networks, they were <lb/>substituted by a unique bridge node (node COA-PWY|UNCLASSIFIED). <lb/>In the range of uncommon bacterial species, we can observe the E. coli module; in the literature, this bacterial <lb/>species has a recognized role in the development of IBD 36,37 . It was possible to observe the different interplay <lb/>between E. coli, V. parvula and B. fragilis across the different diagnoses. The increase of E. coli and B. fragilis in <lb/>IBD was observed in a previous study 38 , but our results provide additional information about the differential <lb/>wiring scheme of the aforementioned species. In particular, it seemed that V. parvula pathways mediated the con-<lb/>nection of E. coli with the other module in the correlation network. In particular, in the NI correlation network, <lb/>V. parvula pathways were in the same module of B. fragilis pathways which were connected to the rest of the <lb/>correlation network. In the CD correlation network, V. parvula pathways were included in the E. coli module, to <lb/>remark how close the two bacterial species were, but if, on the one hand, the relationship between E. coli and B. <lb/>fragilis has been already studied, the effect of V. parvula on E. coli has to be investigated yet in the literature. In <lb/>the UC correlation network, V. parvula formed an almost completely isolated module far from the E. coli, this <lb/>Figure 4. Correlation networks of uncommon metagenomic pathways in (a) NI subjects, (b) CD subjects, (c) <lb/>UC subjects. The nodes encircled show the position of B. fragilis and other species like E. coli and V. parvula. <lb/>The legend remarks the species of each node/pathway, where the grey nodes are classified as &apos; other&apos; . <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>result could differentiate the connectome of the UC microbiome from the connectome of the CD microbiome. <lb/>The isolation of the E. coli module in the UC correlation network could further represent the peculiar features <lb/>of the particular form of IBD. This isolation meant that there were no correlations with the other pathways, and <lb/>the metagenomic expression pattern across the samples correlated only inside the same bacterial species. In <lb/>the NI correlation network, E. siraeum and R. gnavus pathways were the two main bridge pathways between E. <lb/>coli and the rest of the network, it could be possible to hypothesize that re-establishing a connection between <lb/>E. coli module with the aforementioned bacterial species could lead back to healthy gut microbiota. In the CD <lb/>correlation network, R. intestinalis pathways had the role of bridge pathways, and, in fact, by using the permuta-<lb/>tion tests between the NI and CD samples, we obtained that the most differential pathways were R. intestinalis <lb/>pathways. In the literature, this bacterial species, which has anti-inflammatory properties on the intestinal walls, <lb/>was depleted in IBD subjects; nevertheless, the mechanisms underlying its protective action against IBDs are <lb/>still unknown 39,40 . In the uncommon bacterial pathways of the NI projected network, the E. coli module was <lb/>connected to the E. bolteae, which, in turn, was linked to Bifidobacterium longum module. B. longum is a bacte-<lb/>rial species that can have anti-inflammatory properties in the human gut 10 . By contrast, in the CD projected <lb/>network, E. coli was connected to the rest of the network through two Dorea longicatena pathways, which were <lb/>nodes PWY-6163|DOREA_LONGICATENA and COA-PWY-1|DOREA_LONGICATENA and were connected <lb/>Figure 5. Projected network representation of uncommon metagenomic pathways in (a) NI subjects, (b) CD <lb/>subjects, (c) UC subjects. Networks are obtained through a bipartite projection and the exclusion of an edge <lb/>between two nodes is made through a comparison with a null model. The nodes highlighted correspond to <lb/>nodes with high betweenness centralities or to nodes that compare to the NI projected network are isolated. The <lb/>legend remarks the species of each node/pathway, where the grey nodes are classified as &apos; other&apos; . <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>to node PWY-621|ESCHERICHIA_COLI. On the other hand, in the UC projected network, two E. coli nodes <lb/>were connected to six C. comes nodes, showing an interaction between the two species in the UC diagnosis. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Database <lb/>The first step of the workflow (see Fig. 6) starts from the raw data which was taken from the Inflammatory Bowel <lb/>Disease Multi&apos; omics Database (IBDMDB) 41 is one of the first publicly available comprehensive studies of the <lb/>gut ecosystem&apos;s multiple molecular properties involved in the IBD dynamics. Some of the measurements of the <lb/>microbiome offered by the study are metagenomics, metatranscriptomics and metabolomics. The data is related <lb/>to 132 subjects approached in the following five medical centres: Cincinnati Children&apos;s Hospital, Emory Univer-<lb/>sity Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital, Massachusetts General Hospital for Children, and Cedars-Sinai <lb/>Medical Centre. The patients recruited for the study initially arrived at the hospitals either for routine age-related <lb/>colorectal cancer screening, the presence of other gastrointestinal symptoms, or suspected IBD. The latter could <lb/>be a consequence of positive imaging, symptoms of chronic diarrhoea or rectal bleeding. If there were no con-<lb/>ditions for exclusion right after enrolment, a preliminary colonoscopy was performed to determine the study <lb/>strata. Based on initial analyses, the subjects that were not diagnosed with IBD (non-IBD) were labelled as &apos;NI&apos; <lb/>controls. This group of subjects included the patients who arrived for routine screening and those with more <lb/>Figure 6. Diagram representing the methods and the network tools used to analyse the microbiome networks. <lb/>The part surrounded by the dashed line was performed by the IBDMDB. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>benign or non-specific symptoms 42 . The IBDMDB website contains the raw and the final results of the processed <lb/>information, the complete pipeline for producing the final results is: <lb/>1. Quality and error checking for completeness, producing raw files. <lb/>2. AnADAMA pipeline, producing products. <lb/>In particular, if we consider the pipeline for producing the metagenomic data, after stool collection, the samples <lb/>for the quality control process go through the KneadData 43 and the AnADAMA pipelines. The former is a tool <lb/>useful to exclude the reads, which are fragments of DNA, related to the host or related to other contaminants <lb/>from the metagenomic sequencing data, and this separation step is made completely in silico. Whereas the lat-<lb/>ter, the Anadama pipeline, performs and produces documents from an automated scientific workflow, where <lb/>a workflow is simply a succession of tasks, such as quantifying operational taxonomic units (OTU). The OTUs <lb/>are classifications of groups of bacteria closely related to each other by sequence similarity. On the IBDMDB <lb/>website, there are two versions of data Version 2.0 and Version 3.0. Version 3.0 has been uploaded <lb/>with the new version of bioBakery 44 . In our work, we use the products file related to the functional profiles <lb/>Version 2.0. Moreover, we exploit the HMP2 Metadata file, containing the sample IDs, the subject IDs and <lb/>the properties associated with each sample. The External ID is the unique ID of the sample, Partici-<lb/>pant ID is the subject from where the sample has been taken, diagnosis is either ulcerative colitis (UC), <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease (CD) or control group (NI), week_num points out the week number, when the sample has <lb/>been taken and data_type is the type of sample (metagenomics, 16S, etc.). we extracted useful information <lb/>to avoid importing the whole database, and we selected only the samples from the first week (week 0). Moreover, <lb/>the samples different from metagenomic ones were excluded. Finally, we dropped the samples from the same <lb/>participant in week 0 and obtained a list of samples IDs that were present in both the metagenomic database <lb/>and the HMP2 Metadata. The metagenomic database contains as row indexes the gene descriptors; specifi-<lb/>cally, the descriptor is composed of the pathway, genus and species (e.g., &quot;ARO-PWY: chorismate biosynthesis <lb/>I |g__Alistipes.s__Alistipes_finegoldii&quot;). To generate the database, the algorithm HUMAnN2 32 has been used. <lb/>The algorithm can be divided into three phases; firstly, the metagenomic sample is quickly analyzed to seek <lb/>known species in the gut microbiome. The functional annotation of the identified pangenomes (i.e. the genome <lb/>of a larger group of species) of the microbiome is concatenated to form a gene database of the sample. Secondly, <lb/>using this database, the whole sample is aligned, meaning that statistics regarding the species and the genes are <lb/>made, and unmapped reads are collected. Thirdly, the gene abundances are calculated, and they are combined <lb/>with the metabolic network to determine the pathways in the microbial community. <lb/>To reduce the number of pathways present in the resulting network, we built the correlation matrices and <lb/>the biadjacency matrices for the projected networks for three different groups of pathways based on quantiles; <lb/>namely, one group for the pathways expressed in a percentage between 25% and 50% of the subjects (uncommon <lb/>pathways), another group for those in the range between 50% and 75% (common pathways), and lastly a group <lb/>for the pathways expressed in more than 75% (prevalent pathways). Originally, there were 953 nodes among the <lb/>uncommon pathways. 43 nodes were disconnected from the rest of the network in the correlation networks, <lb/>hence, we chose to exclude these pathways from our analysis in both the correlation and projected networks. <lb/>Correlation Networks <lb/>Correlation networks are built from the following steps: <lb/>1. pairwise gene similarity score (correlation); <lb/>2. thresholding. <lb/>Normalization methods, correlation measures (Pearson or Spearman), significance and relevance are still <lb/>debated 45 . In our work, we chose the Pearson correlation similar to Ref. 46 . <lb/>To transform a correlation matrix into a correlation network, we used a thresholding method inspired by a <lb/>brain network technique that was used to cut the least important edges and keep the significant relationships <lb/>among the nodes, hence, we calculated the absolute value of the correlations, making the signs irrelevant. This <lb/>method consists of increasing a cut-off threshold until the network connectivity breaks apart; because of this <lb/>property, this cut-off threshold is also known as the percolation threshold. This method has been considered <lb/>one of the most effective methods to maximise the information quantity kept by the network 47 . In our work, we <lb/>started from a cut-off threshold of t = 0 , and we used a bisection method to get to the percolation threshold. <lb/>In the bisection method, we flattened the absolute values in the weighted adjacency matrix into a sorted array, <lb/>chose the median value and used it as the new cut-off threshold, we calculated the connectivity of the graph <lb/>built from the adjacency matrix having this cut-off threshold, finally, if we obtained a connected graph with the <lb/>median value as a cut-off threshold, we used as the sorted array the upper half array, on the contrary, we used <lb/>the lower half. The procedure was iterative until convergence which corresponded to an array with zero length <lb/>or with the same head and same tail. <lb/>Co-expression network from bipartite projected networks <lb/>Bipartite networks are graphs G = (U, V , E) where the nodes can be divided into two disjoint sets, U and V, and <lb/>every edge in E links an element in U to an element in V. In our work, we designated with U the set of nodes <lb/>representing the genes and with V the set of nodes representing the samples. We can find in E all the edges con-<lb/>necting the gene u to the sample v if the gene was over-expressed in the corresponding sample. We evaluated <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>the over-expression of a gene through the binarization of the data that led to the construction of a biadjacency <lb/>matrix B of size |U| × |V | that described the bipartite network G = (U, V , E) with the entries (0, 1), where B ij = 1 <lb/>if the gene v i is over-expressed in the sample u j , and B ij = 0 if it is not over-expressed. Biadjacency matrices are <lb/>rectangular matrices where on one side there are the nodes in U, and on the other side the nodes in V. <lb/>Binarization <lb/>The binarization process is useful to highlight the edges in E that are over-expressed. By using the revealed <lb/>comparative advantage (RCA) 48 , We highlighted the over-expressed genes for specific samples: <lb/>where E is the expression of the gene i in the sample j. When RCA ij &gt; 1 , the quantity of gene i in sample j can <lb/>be considered over-expressed and the entry b ij = 1 (where b ij is the element of the final biadjacency matrix), in <lb/>the other case RCA ij ≤ 1 , then b ij = 0. <lb/>Randomization of bipartite networks <lb/>To generate a null model useful to calculate the statistically important properties of a real bipartite network, we <lb/>randomized the bipartite networks by using the package BiCM 49 . In particular, the package is based on the works <lb/>by Ref. 50-52 . In the aforementioned works, the Shannon entropy is defined as <lb/>is maximized, where G is an ensemble of binary, undirected, bipartite networks, and <lb/>-→ <lb/>C (M) is a given set of <lb/>constraints. The result is: <lb/>Where H M, <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ = <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ • <lb/>-→ <lb/>C (M) is the Hamiltonian and Z <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ = M∈G e <lb/>-H M, <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ is the normalization. In <lb/>the case of the bipartite extension of the configuration model (BiCM), the Hamiltonian becomes: <lb/>because we have two layers of nodes and we constrained the degree sequences <lb/>-→ <lb/>d (M) and -→ u (M) . <lb/>-→ <lb/>d (M) is the <lb/>degree sequence of the genes and -→ u (M) is the degree sequence of the samples. <lb/>Projection <lb/>One way to compress the information contained in a bipartite network is to project the bipartite network onto <lb/>one of the two layers (gene/pathway layer or sample layer). We carried out the projection by connecting in the <lb/>same layer the nodes that were linked by a common node in the other layer. The projection leads to a loss of <lb/>information itself, so to avoid further loss of information, we weighted the edges by the number of common <lb/>nodes neighbouring the nodes in the same layer 53 . The algorithm to perform the projection is: <lb/>1. select the partition on which the projection will be done <lb/>2. take two nodes of the selected partition, n and n ′ , and calculate their similarity <lb/>3. by evaluating the corresponding p-value compute the statistical significance of the calculated similarity with <lb/>respect to a properly-defined null model; <lb/>4. if, and only if, the p-value associated with the link n and n ′ is statistically significant, connect the selected <lb/>nodes. <lb/>The similarity in the second step of the algorithm is evaluated by: <lb/>where V c <lb/>nn ′ ≡ m nc m n ′ c and it is clear from the definition that V c <lb/>nn ′ = 1 if, and only if, both n and n ′ are common <lb/>neighbours of c. The third step of the algorithm passes through the calculation of the p-value of the Poisson-<lb/>Binomial distribution, i.e. the probability of observing a number of V-motifs greater than, or equal to, the <lb/>observed one (which will be indicated as V * <lb/>nn ′ : <lb/>(1) <lb/>RCA ij = <lb/>E ij / j ′ ∈V E ij ′ <lb/>i ′ ∈U E i ′ j / i ′ ∈U,j ′ ∈V E i ′ j ′ <lb/>(2) <lb/>S = -<lb/>M∈G <lb/>P(M) ln P(M) <lb/>(3) <lb/>P M| <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ = <lb/>e <lb/>-H M, <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ <lb/>Z <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ <lb/>(4) <lb/>H M, <lb/>-→ <lb/>θ = -→ α • <lb/>-→ <lb/>d (M) + <lb/>-→ <lb/>β -→ u (M) <lb/>(5) <lb/>V nn ′ = <lb/>N c <lb/>c=1 <lb/>m nc m n ′ c = <lb/>N c <lb/>c=1 <lb/>V c <lb/>nn ′ , <lb/>(6) <lb/>p -value(V * <lb/>nn ′ ) = <lb/>V nn ′ ≥V * <lb/>nn ′ <lb/>f PB (V nn ′ ) = 1 -<lb/>V nn ′ ≤V * <lb/>nn ′ <lb/>f PB (V nn ′ ). <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>
			
			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Finally, in the last step of the algorithm, in order to understand which p-values were significant, a false-discovery <lb/>rate or FDR has been adopted to take into account the fact that we were testing multiple hypotheses 54 . <lb/>Betweenness centrality <lb/>There are many different centrality measures in network science, namely degree centrality, betweenness central-<lb/>ity, and eigenvector centrality; these measures describe the importance of a node in the network. In our work, <lb/>we considered only the betweenness centrality, because it was the most suited to represent the importance of <lb/>the pathways, i.e. the nodes. The betweenness centrality was introduced by Freeman 55 , and it considers more <lb/>important the nodes that behave as bridges in the network. It can be calculated as: <lb/>where σ st is the number of shortest paths connecting s and t, whilst σ st (i) is the number of shortest paths con-<lb/>necting s and t and going through i. <lb/>Community detection <lb/>In the study of network science, both natural complex networks and artificial complex networks display a modu-<lb/>lar behaviour, i.e. groups of nodes are more densely connected within the members of the group than with the <lb/>rest of the network. This phenomenon can also be described by a function called modularity 56 , which can be <lb/>used as a parameter for one of the several ways to perform community detection in complex networks. In our <lb/>work, we used the Louvain method 57 because it is suited to large complex networks, moreover, this method is <lb/>usually used when it is assumed that the gut microbiome of a healthy subject is a singular assortative network 58 . <lb/>We hypothesized that the modularity changes if the network represents the gut microbiome of an IBD subject. <lb/>Louvain method is based on an optimization problem that can be solved in a time O(n • log 2 n) where n is the <lb/>number of nodes in the network 59 . The method is based on the aforementioned modularity optimization. Modu-<lb/>larity is defined as in Ref. 60 , <lb/>The algorithm is based on two phases that repeat iteratively. In the first phase, each node is repeatedly moved <lb/>individually between the communities to maximize modularity. The first phase stops when no further individual <lb/>move can improve the modularity. In the second phase, each community formed in the first phase is considered <lb/>as a node of a weighted graph, where the weights of the edges are given by the sum of the edges connecting the <lb/>nodes in the communities. The algorithm has a high efficiency partly because the gain modularity Q , due to <lb/>moving a node i into a community C, can be steadily calculated as: <lb/>where in is the sum of the weights of the edges inside C, tot is the sum of the weights of the edges going from <lb/>the outside to the nodes inside C, k i is the sum of the weights of the edges going to node i, and k i,in is the sum of <lb/>the weights of the edges going from i to the nodes in C and, finally, m is the sum of the weights of all the edges <lb/>in the graph. One of the limitations of community detection based on modularity is the resolution limit 61 . This <lb/>limitation to modularity may be present when l s ≈ <lb/>√ <lb/>2L , where l s is the number of internal links in a module S <lb/>and L is the total number of links in the network and it can be overcome through several methods, one of the <lb/>most promising is Surprise maximization 62 . The modularity in correlation networks differs from the modularity <lb/>in projected networks mainly because, in the former networks, the information being represented is based on <lb/>the covariance of the pathway expressions across all the subjects, whereas, in the latter networks, the information <lb/>is built on a cumulative measure that counts the number of subjects sharing common pathways. Therefore, in <lb/>the first case, community detection identifies groups of correlated pathways and, in the second case, it identifies <lb/>pathways that often appear in the same subject. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on <lb/>reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 16 August 2022; Accepted: 29 October 2023 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Sender, R., Fuchs, S. &amp; Milo, R. Revised estimates for the number of human and bacteria cells in the body. PLoS Biol. 14, e1002533 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>2. Thursby, E. &amp; Juge, N. Introduction to the human gut microbiota. Biochem. J. 474, 1823-1836 (2017). <lb/>3. Tanaka, M. &amp; Nakayama, J. Development of the gut microbiota in infancy and its impact on health in later life. Allergol. Int. 66, <lb/>515-522 (2017). <lb/>4. Ma, Y., Chen, H., Lan, C. &amp; Ren, J. Help, hope and hype: Ethical considerations of human microbiome research and applications. <lb/>Protein Cell 9, 404-415 (2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>(7) <lb/>C B (i) = <lb/>s� =t� =i∈V <lb/>σ st (i) <lb/>σ st <lb/>(8) <lb/>Q = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m i,j <lb/>A ij -<lb/>k i k j <lb/>2m <lb/>δ(c i , c j ). <lb/>(9) <lb/>Q = <lb/>in +k i,in <lb/>2m <lb/>-<lb/>tot +k i <lb/>2m <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>in <lb/>2m <lb/>-<lb/>tot <lb/>2m <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>k i <lb/>2m <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>5. Farré-Maduell, E. &amp; Casals-Pascual, C. The origins of gut microbiome research in Europe: From Escherich to Nissle. Hum. Micro-<lb/>biome J. 14, 100065 (2019). <lb/>6. Natividad, J. M. M. &amp; Verdu, E. F. Modulation of intestinal barrier by intestinal microbiota: Pathological and therapeutic implica-<lb/>tions. Pharmacol. Res. 69, 42-51 (2013). <lb/>7. Sommer, F. &amp; Bäckhed, F. The gut microbiota-masters of host development and physiology. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 11, 227-238 (2013). <lb/>8. Belizário, J. E. &amp; Faintuch, J. Microbiome and gut dysbiosis. In Metabolic Interaction in Infection, 459-476 (Springer, 2018). <lb/>9. Borody, T. J. &amp; Khoruts, A. Fecal microbiota transplantation and emerging applications. Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 9, 88-96 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>10. Singh, S. et al. Common symptoms and stressors among individuals with inflammatory bowel diseases. Clin. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. <lb/>9, 769-775 (2011). <lb/>11. Ananthakrishnan, A. N., Xavier, R. J. &amp; Podolsky, D. K. Inflammatory Bowel Diseases: A Clinician&apos;s Guide (Wiley, New York, 2017). <lb/>12. Manichanh, C., Borruel, N., Casellas, F. &amp; Guarner, F. The gut microbiota in IBD. Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 9, 599-608 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>13. Kirsner, J. B. Historical aspects of inflammatory bowel disease. J. Clin. gastroenterol. 10, 286-297 (1988). <lb/>14. Kaplan, G. G. The global burden of IBD: From 2015 to 2025. Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 12, 720-727 (2015). <lb/>15. Xavier, R. J. &amp; Podolsky, D. K. Unravelling the pathogenesis of inflammatory bowel disease. Nature 448, 427-434 (2007). <lb/>16. Lees, C. W. &amp; Satsangi, J. Genetics of inflammatory bowel disease: Implications for disease pathogenesis and natural history. Expert <lb/>Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 3, 513-534 (2009). <lb/>17. Zhang, Y.-Z. &amp; Li, Y.-Y. Inflammatory bowel disease: Pathogenesis. World J. Gastroenterol. WJG 20, 91 (2014). <lb/>18. Fiocchi, C. &amp; Iliopoulos, D. IBD systems biology is here to stay. Inflamm. Bowel Dis. 27, 760-770 (2021). <lb/>19. De Souza, H. S. P., Fiocchi, C. &amp; Iliopoulos, D. The IBD interactome: An integrated view of aetiology, pathogenesis and therapy. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 14, 739-749 (2017). <lb/>20. Barabási, A.-L., Gulbahce, N. &amp; Loscalzo, J. Network medicine: A network-based approach to human disease. Nat. Rev. Genet. 12, <lb/>56 (2011). <lb/>21. Faust, K. et al. Signatures of ecological processes in microbial community time series. Microbiome 6, 1-13 (2018). <lb/>22. Bucci, V. et al. MDSINE: Microbial Dynamical Systems INference Engine for microbiome time-series analyses. Genome Biol. 17, <lb/>1-17 (2016). <lb/>23. Coyte, K. Z. &amp; Rakoff-Nahoum, S. Understanding competition and cooperation within the mammalian gut microbiome. Current <lb/>Biol. 29, R538-R544 (2019). <lb/>24. Vernocchi, P. et al. Network analysis of gut microbiome and metabolome to discover microbiota-linked biomarkers in patients <lb/>affected by non-small cell lung cancer. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 21, 8730 (2020). <lb/>25. Bauer, E. &amp; Thiele, I. From network analysis to functional metabolic modeling of the human gut microbiota. MSystems 3, 00209-17 <lb/>(2018). <lb/>26. Stein, R. R. et al. Ecological modeling from time-series inference: Insight into dynamics and stability of intestinal microbiota. PLoS <lb/>Comput. Biol. 9, e1003388. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1371/ journ al. pcbi. 10033 88 (2013). <lb/>27. Chen, L. et al. Gut microbial co-abundance networks show specificity in inflammatory bowel disease and obesity. Nat. Commun. <lb/>11, 1-12 (2020). <lb/>28. Friedman, J. &amp; Alm, E. J. Inferring correlation networks from genomic survey data. PLoS Comput. Biol. 8(9), e1002687 (2012). <lb/>29. Weiss, S. et al. Correlation detection strategies in microbial data sets vary widely in sensitivity and precision. ISME J. 10, 1669-1681 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>30. Karp, P. D. et al. The biocyc collection of microbial genomes and metabolic pathways. Brief. Bioinform. 20, 1085-1093 (2019). <lb/>31. Caspi, R. et al. The MetaCyc database of metabolic pathways and enzymes and the BioCyc collection of Pathway/Genome Databases. <lb/>Nucl. Acids Res. 42, D459-D471. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1093/ nar/ gkt11 03 (2013). <lb/>32. Franzosa, E. A. et al. Species-level functional profiling of metagenomes and metatranscriptomes. Nat. Methods 15, 962-968 (2018). <lb/>33. Cao, Y., Shen, J. &amp; Ran, Z. H. Association between Faecalibacterium prausnitzii reduction and inflammatory bowel disease: A <lb/>meta-analysis and systematic review of the literature. Gastroenterol. Res. Pract. 2014 (2014). <lb/>34. Xi, M. et al. Effects of stachyose on intestinal microbiota and immunity in mice infected with enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli. J. <lb/>Funct. Foods 64, 103689 (2020). <lb/>35. Zhou, Y. &amp; Zhi, F. Lower level of bacteroides in the gut microbiota is associated with inflammatory bowel disease: A meta-analysis. <lb/>BioMed. Res. Int.https:// doi. org/ 10. 1155/ 2016/ 58289 59 (2016). <lb/>36. Rhodes, J. M. The role of Escherichia coli in inflammatory bowel disease. Gut 56, 610-612 (2007). <lb/>37. Schirmer, M., Garner, A., Vlamakis, H. &amp; Xavier, R. J. Microbial genes and pathways in inflammatory bowel disease. Nat. Rev. <lb/>Microbiol. 17, 497-511 (2019). <lb/>38. Keighley, M. R. et al. Influence of inflammatory bowel disease on intestinal microflora. Gut 19, 1099-1104 (1978). <lb/>39. Zhu, C. et al. Roseburia intestinalis inhibits interleukin-17 excretion and promotes regulatory T cells differentiation in colitis. Mol. <lb/>Med. Rep. 17, 7567-7574 (2018). <lb/>40. Hoffmann, T. W. et al. Microorganisms linked to inflammatory bowel disease-associated dysbiosis differentially impact host <lb/>physiology in gnotobiotic mice. ISME J. 10, 460-477 (2016). <lb/>41. IBDMDB -Home | IBDMDB. <lb/>42. Lloyd-Price, J. et al. Multi-omics of the gut microbial ecosystem in inflammatory bowel diseases. Nature 569, 655-662. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1038/ s41586-019-1237-9 (2019). <lb/>43. KneadData -The Huttenhower Lab. <lb/>44. McIver, L. J. et al. BioBakery: A meta&apos; omic analysis environment. Bioinformatics 34, 1235-1237. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1093/ bioin forma <lb/>tics/ btx754 (2018). <lb/>45. Tieri, P. et al. Network inference and reconstruction in bioinformatics. In Encyclopedia of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology <lb/>(2019). <lb/>46. MacMahon, M. &amp; Garlaschelli, D. Community detection for correlation matrices. arXiv: 1311. 1924 (2013). <lb/>47. Nicolini, C., Forcellini, G., Minati, L. &amp; Bifone, A. Scale-resolved analysis of brain functional connectivity networks with spectral <lb/>entropy. NeuroImage 211, 116603 (2020). <lb/>48. Balassa, B. Trade liberalisation and &quot;revealed&apos;&apos; comparative advantage 1. Manch. Sch. 33, 99-123 (1965). <lb/>49. Bruno, M. BiCM: Python package for the computation of the Bipartite Configuration Model. (2020). <lb/>50. Squartini, T. &amp; Garlaschelli, D. Analytical maximum-likelihood method to detect patterns in real networks. New J. Phys. 13, 83001 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>51. Saracco, F., Di Clemente, R., Gabrielli, A. &amp; Squartini, T. Randomizing bipartite networks: The case of the World Trade Web. Sci. <lb/>Rep. 5, 1-18. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ srep1 0595 (2015). <lb/>52. Saracco, F. et al. Inferring monopartite projections of bipartite networks: An entropy-based approach. New J. Phys. 19, 53022 <lb/>(2017). <lb/>53. Neal, Z. The backbone of bipartite projections: Inferring relationships from co-authorship, co-sponsorship, co-attendance and <lb/>other co-behaviors. Soc. Netw. 39, 84-97 (2014). <lb/>54. Benjamini, Y. &amp; Hochberg, Y. Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. J. R. Stat. <lb/>Soc. Ser. B (Methodol.) 57, 289-300 (1995). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>
			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:19428 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46184-y <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>55. Freeman, L. C. A set of measures of centrality based on betweenness. Sociometry 40, 35-41 (1977). <lb/>56. Newman, M. E. J. Modularity and community structure in networks. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 103, 8577-8582 (2006). <lb/>57. Blondel, V. D., Guillaume, J.-L., Lambiotte, R. &amp; Lefebvre, E. Fast unfolding of communities in large networks. J. Stat. Mech. Theory <lb/>Exp. 2008, P10008 (2008). <lb/>58. Hall, C. V. et al. Co-existence of network architectures supporting the human gut microbiome. Iscience 22, 380-391 (2019). <lb/>59. Lancichinetti, A. &amp; Fortunato, S. Community detection algorithms: A comparative analysis. Phys. Rev. E 80, 56117 (2009). <lb/>60. Newman, M. E. J. Analysis of weighted networks. Phys. Rev. E 70, 56131 (2004). <lb/>61. Fortunato, S. &amp; Barthelemy, M. Resolution limit in community detection. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 104, 36-41 (2007). <lb/>62. Aldecoa, R. &amp; Marín, I. Surprise maximization reveals the community structure of complex networks. Sci. Rep. 3, 1-9 (2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>Conceptualization, G.C., T.G. and M.H.; methodology, G.C., T.G. and M.H.; software, M.H. and T.G.; validation, <lb/>M.H. and T.G.; formal analysis, M.H.; investigation, M.H.; resources, M.H.; data curation, M.H.; writing-origi-<lb/>nal draft preparation, M.H.; writing-review and editing, T.G. and G.C.; visualization, M.H.; supervision, M.H., <lb/>T.G. and G.C.; project administration, G.C.; funding acquisition, G.C. All authors have read and agreed to the <lb/>published version of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Additional information <lb/>Supplementary Information The online version contains supplementary material available at https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1038/ s41598-023-46184-y. <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to G.C. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the <lb/>Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from <lb/>the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http:// creat iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2023 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
