<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 <lb/>| https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>Polypropylene microplastics <lb/>promote metastatic features <lb/>in human breast cancer <lb/>Jun Hyung Park 1,5 , Seungwoo Hong 2,5 , Ok-Hyeon Kim 3 , Chul-Hong Kim 4 , Jinho Kim 4 , <lb/>Jung-Woong Kim 4* , Sungguan Hong 2* &amp; Hyun Jung Lee 1,3* <lb/>Microplastics (MPs) are now a global issue due to increased plastic production and use. Recently, <lb/>various studies have been performed in response to the human health risk assessment. However, <lb/>these studies have focused on spherical MPs, which have smooth edges and a spherical shape and <lb/>account for less than 1% of MPs in nature. Unfortunately, studies on fragment-type MPs are very <lb/>limited and remain in the initial stages. In this study, we studied the effect that 16.4 µm fragment <lb/>type polypropylene (PP) MPs, which have an irregular shape and sharp edges and form naturally in <lb/>the environment, had on breast cancer. The detrimental effects of PPMPs on breast cancer metastasis <lb/>were examined. Here, 1.6 mg/ml of PPMP, which does not induce cytotoxicity in MDA-MB-231, was <lb/>used, and at this concentration, PPMP did not induce morphological changes or cellular migrating <lb/>in the MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 cells. However, PPMP incubation for 24 hours in the MDA-MB-231 <lb/>cells significantly altered the level of cell cycle-related transcripts in an RNA-seq analysis. When <lb/>confirmed by qRT-PCR, the gene expression of TMBIM6, AP2M1, and PTP4A2 was increased, while the <lb/>transcript level of FTH1 was decreased. Further, secretion of the pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-6 from <lb/>cancer cells was elevated with the incubation of PPMP for 12 hours. These results suggest that PPMP <lb/>enhances metastasis-related gene expression and cytokines in breast cancer cells, exacerbating breast <lb/>cancer metastasis. <lb/>Abbreviations <lb/>MP <lb/>Microplastic <lb/>SEM <lb/>Scanning electron microscopy <lb/>PBS <lb/>Phosphate buffered saline <lb/>HMDS <lb/>Hexamethyldisilazane <lb/>HPLC/DAD High-performance liquid chromatography/diode array detector <lb/>qRT-PCR <lb/>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction <lb/>ELISA <lb/>Enzyme-linked immunoassay <lb/>ER <lb/>Estrogen receptor <lb/>PR <lb/>Progesterone receptor <lb/>HER2 <lb/>Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 <lb/>Microplastics (MPs) are typically less than 5 mm in size and are not only derived from the degradation of plastic <lb/>objects in the environment but are also produced for commercial uses 1,2 . Recently, MPs have been deemed a <lb/>new environmental pollutant due to their increased production and extremely low natural biodegradation in <lb/>the ecosystem 3 . There are increasing reports of MPs in drinking water and food products, including sea salt, due <lb/>to their broad range in shape and size and the number of polymers in the oceans and freshwater ecosystems 4-6 . <lb/>Importantly, MPs can enter the human body via the accumulation of MPs in the food chain. It was reported that <lb/>MPs had been detected in the gastrointestinal tract of marine animals and human tissue and organs 7,8 . <lb/>OPEN <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Global Innovative Drugs, Graduate School of Chung-Ang University, Seoul 06974, South <lb/>Korea. 2 Department of Chemistry, College of Natural Sciences, Chung-Ang University, Seoul 06974, South <lb/>Korea. 3 Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, College of Medicine, Chung-Ang University, Seoul 06974, South <lb/>Korea. 4 Department of Life Sciences, Chung-Ang University, Seoul 06974, South Korea. 5 These authors contributed <lb/>equally: Jun Hyung Park and Seungwoo Hong. * email: jungkim@cau.ac.kr; sungguanhong@cau.ac.kr; pluto38@ <lb/>cau.ac.kr <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>MPs pose significant environmental and health concerns because of their persistence in the environment, <lb/>potential toxicity, and ability to absorb contaminants and pathogens from the environment. However, the long-<lb/>term effects of MPs on human health are currently unknown 9 . Most studies that examined the health effects of <lb/>MPs have used animal subjects. The ingestion of MPs has been shown to cause an inflammatory response and <lb/>can damage the gut, disrupt gut microorganisms, cause organ damage, and affect reproduction and metabolism. <lb/>Breathing in MPs can cause inflammation and chemical toxicity and introduce pathogenic microorganisms into <lb/>the body. MPs introduced through skin contact can cause skin damage due to local inflammation and cellular <lb/>toxicity 10 . <lb/>Notably, the use of face masks made of synthetic fibers and disposable food containers during the corona-<lb/>virus disease of 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic may have contributed to the exposure of MPs 11,12 . Further, most <lb/>plastic products have been known to release estrogenic chemicals or endocrine-disrupting chemicals (EDCs) 13 . <lb/>Exposure to EDCs and estrogenic chemicals may increase the risk of cancer or metabolic syndromes, including <lb/>obesity 11,14 . Currently, there is a lack of evidence on the actual risks of MPs relating to cancer development or <lb/>metabolic diseases, despite claims in scientific articles. This study evaluated the effect of polypropylene MPS <lb/>(PPMPs) on human breast cancer cells. We found that moderate amounts of PPMPs significantly accelerated the <lb/>cell cycle of cancer cells and enhanced the secretion of interleukin 6 (IL-6) in the human breast cancer cell lines, <lb/>MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7; however, cellular migration and motility were not altered. In addition, our RNAseq <lb/>analysis revealed that PPMPs affected cancer cell-matrix adhesion and cell cycle-related signaling in human breast <lb/>cancer. Consequently, chronic exposure to PPMPs may increase the risk of cancer progression and metastasis. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Preparation of PPMPs. Polypropylene pellets (PPs) were purchased from the Namyang Corporation <lb/>(Korea). Pellets were crushed thoroughly by a cryogenic grinder. We used a 6875D Freezer/Mill (SPEX Sam-<lb/>plePrep, United States) at the National Instrumentation Center for Environmental Management, Seoul National <lb/>University (Korea). Then, the powder from the crushed PPs was filtered and collected based on particle size <lb/>using a 100 μm-micropore nickel base sieve (Precision Eforming, United States). <lb/>Particle size analysis. The particle size distribution plot of the PPs used in this study was calculated based <lb/>on the data from the particle size analyzer. We used a Mastersizer 3000 (Malvern Panalytical, United Kingdom) <lb/>at the Center for Biotechnology Facilities, Chung-Ang University (Korea). The automatic dry dispersion method <lb/>was selected to detect the most pristine form of the MP particles. <lb/>Scanning electron microscopy (SEM). The medium was replaced with medium with or without PPMPs <lb/>at 1.6 mg/ml, and incubated at 37 °C in 5% CO 2 for 24 hours. Cells were washed with phosphate buffered saline <lb/>(PBS) and fixed in 2% glutaraldehyde (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) for 1 hour. The cells underwent a graded ethanol <lb/>dehydration series (50, 75, 90, 95, 100%) for ten minutes each. Cells were subsequently immersed in a 1:1 etha-<lb/>nol/hexamethyldisilazane (HMDS, Sigma-Aldrich, USA), 1:2 ethanol/HMDS, and 100% HMDS for 5 minutes <lb/>each. The samples were mounted on stubs, coated with a layer of platinum, and viewed using an S-3400N micro-<lb/>scope (Hitachi, Japan) at 10 kV. <lb/>High-performance liquid chromatography-diode array detection (HPLC-DAD) analysis. All <lb/>samples were analyzed using an Agilent 1260 infinity II high-performance liquid chromatography/diode array <lb/>detector (HPLC/DAD) system consisting of quaternary pumps (G7111A), a G7129A autosampler, a G7116A <lb/>column oven, and a G7115A diode array detector. Data analysis was performed by the Agilent openlab CDS <lb/>chemstation software (version: C.01.10[201]). HPLC analysis was performed on an Eclipse XDB-C18 column <lb/>(250 mm × 4.6 mm, 5 μm). Isocratic elution was carried out using a mobile phase consisting of a mixture of 0.1% <lb/>acetic acid in water and 0.1% acetic acid in acetonitrile (a ratio of 70:30). The monitoring wavelength ranged <lb/>from 200 to 400 nm. Detection was performed using wavelengths of 210, 254, and 350 nm. An injection volume <lb/>of 10 μL was used. The total running time was 60 minutes. <lb/>Cell culture. The human breast cancer cell lines MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 were purchased from the Ameri-<lb/>can Type Culture Collection (ATCC, USA). MCF-7 cells were cultured in Dulbecco&apos;s modified essential medium <lb/>(DMEM, Welgene, Korea) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Abfrontier, Korea) and 1% penicil-<lb/>lin/streptomycin (Gibco, USA). MDA-MB-231 cells were cultured in Roswell Park Memorial Institute medium <lb/>(RPMI) 1640 (Welgene, Korea) containing 10% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomycin at 37 °C in 5% CO 2 (v/v). <lb/>Sterilization was performed in consideration of the melting point of polypropylene (about 160 degrees). Before <lb/>the experiment, PPMPs were sterilized by autoclaving at 121 °C for 15 minutes and UV treatment for 30 minutes. <lb/>Sterilized PPMPs were mixed with cell medium at a concentration of 1.6 mg/ml and sonicated for 30 minutes to <lb/>be added to the cell culture. The observed PPMPs did not aggregate together. <lb/>Cell viability. Cell viability was assessed using the AlamarBlue assay kit (Invitrogen, USA) following the <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions. MDA-MB-231 cells were seeded onto 96-well culture plates (Thermo Fisher Scien-<lb/>tific, USA) at a density of 5 × 10 3 cells per well and allowed to adhere overnight. Various concentrations (0, 0.4, <lb/>0.8, 1.2, 1.6 and 2.0 mg/ml) of PPMPs were added to each well, and the cells were incubated for 24 hours. At the <lb/>end of the experiment, 10% (v/v) AlamarBlue solution was added to each well. After a 2-hour incubation, the <lb/>fluorescence intensity was measured by a Synergy LX Multi-Mode Reader (Agilent Technologies, USA) at excita-<lb/>tion and emission wavelengths of 530 and 590 nm, respectively. All assays were performed with three replicates. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Time-lapse imaging. For the cell migration tracking experiments, a six-well plate (SPL, Korea) was placed <lb/>on an inverted microscope (Eclipse Ti2, Nikon, Japan). The medium was replaced with medium with or without <lb/>PPMPs at 1.6 mg/ml, and then breast cancer cells, MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 motility was observed. Images <lb/>were recorded every three minutes for 6 hours in a chamber maintained at 37 °C with 5% CO 2 . Cells were <lb/>tracked by time-lapse image sequences using the manual tracking plug-in for Image J (http:// rsb. info. nih. gov/ ij). <lb/>The Image J output was integrated into the Chemotaxis and Migration Tool software (ibidi GmbH, Germany) to <lb/>determine the migration position and velocity of the cells in each well. The total distances and average velocities <lb/>were obtained from 360 cells for each group (30 cells for each position, 4 positions per sample, 3 independent <lb/>experiments). <lb/>Wound healing. For the wound healing migration assay, cells were seeded onto a 24-well plate and allowed <lb/>to grow to form a confluent monolayer. MDA-MB-213 and MCF-7 human breast cancer cells were wounded <lb/>with a 200 µL pipette tip. After wounding, the detached cells were removed, the medium was replaced with <lb/>culture media containing a vehicle or 1.6 mg/ml PPMPs, and cells were further incubated for 12 hours. Images <lb/>of the wound gap were monitored under a phase-contrast microscope (IX-81, Olympus, Japan), and the wound <lb/>closure was measured using Image J software (http:// rsb. info. nih. gov/ ij). <lb/>RNA-sequencing and bioinformatic analysis. The RNA-seq library was generated using the TruSeq <lb/>mRNA Library Prep Kit (Illumina, Inc., USA) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Briefly, total RNA <lb/>(50 ng) from the MDA-MB-231 cells (which treated MP medium for 24 hours the previous day) was isolated, a 5&apos; <lb/>oligo-dT primer was hybridized to the RNA, and reverse transcription was carried out. Second-strand synthesis <lb/>was initiated with a random primer containing an Illumina-compatible linker sequence at its 5&apos; end. The double-<lb/>stranded library was purified with AMPure magnetic beads (A63881, Beckman coulter, CA, USA) to remove <lb/>all the reaction components. High-throughput sequencing was carried out as paired-end 101 sequencing reads <lb/>using a NovaSeq 6000 (Illumina, Inc., USA). mRNA-Seq reads were aligned using STAR-2.7.1a. The alignment <lb/>file was applied for assembling transcripts, estimating their abundances, and detecting the differential expression <lb/>of genes. We perform read feature counting with RNA-Seq by expectation-maximization (RSEM) (v.1.3.3), and <lb/>the fragments per kilobase of transcript per million fragments mapped (FPKM) were calculated using the FPKM <lb/>function from DESeq2 (v.1.32.0). The differential transcripts and genes expression were filtered by absolute log2 <lb/>fold-change [log2 FC] &gt; 1 and p-value &lt; 0.01 by edgeR (v.3.36.0). The significant DEGs/DETs were found by <lb/>more strict criteria abs(log2 FC &gt; 1.5) and p-value &lt; 0.01. Gene ontology (GO) and pathway analysis were per-<lb/>formed by DAVID (PMID: 35325185). <lb/>qRT-PCR. Total RNA was extracted from 8 × 10 5 of MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 cells using the RNeasy Mini <lb/>kit (QIAGEN, Germany), according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Reverse transcription of the RNA was <lb/>performed using the Maxima First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit for qRT-PCR (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA). <lb/>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was performed using the Power SYBR Green PCR <lb/>Master Mix reagent (Applied Biosystems) and StepOne Plus real-time PCR kit (Applied Biosystems). For cal-<lb/>culating the fold change, the cycle thresholds (Cts) were determined using the StepOne software v.2.3 (Applied <lb/>Biosystems), and mRNA expression was normalized to the GAPDH transcript and the control sample. The <lb/>primer sequences of the various genes were as follows: TMBIM6 (Forward: 5′-AGA GCT TCA GTG TGA GAG <lb/>GA-3′; Reverse: 5′-GCA GCT AAA TCA GAG GAC AG-3′), AP2M1 (Forward: 5′-CAA GCA AGA GCG GGA AGC <lb/>-3′; Reverse: 5′-CCA TCT GGC GGG ATA AAG C-3′), PTP4A2 (Forward: 5 GGA ATC CAC GTT CTA GAT TGGC-<lb/>3′; Reverse: 5′-AAC ACA GCA ACC TGG CTC TT-3′), FTH1 (Forward: 5′-CTC CTA CGT TTA CCT GTC CA-3′; <lb/>Reverse: 5′-CTC TCC CAG TCA TCA CAG TC-3′), and GAPDH (Forward: 5′-CAG CCT CAA GAT CAT CAG <lb/>CA-3′; Reverse: 5′-TGT GGT CAT GAG TCC TTC CA-3′). <lb/>Enzyme-linked immunoassay (ELISA). Cells were seeded in 100 mm culture dishes at a density of 8 × <lb/>10 5 cells/ml, cultured until 90% confluence, and then replaced with or without PPMPs medium at a concentra-<lb/>tion of 1.6mg/ml. Following a 24-hour incubation at 37 °C, the supernatant was collected and analyzed for IL-6 <lb/>levels using the CymaxTM Human IL-6 enzyme-linked immunoassay (ELISA) KIT (Abfrontier, Korea) follow-<lb/>ing the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Cell-cycle progression with immunofluorescence/proliferation. The cell cycle analysis was per-<lb/>formed using a Premo FUCCI Cell Cycle Sensor BacMam 2.0 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA). MCF-7 cells <lb/>were seeded on a six-well plate at a density of 10 4 cells per well. When the cells were completely attached, the <lb/>Premo™ reagent (geminin-GFP, Cdt1-RFP), at a volume of 20 particles per cell, was transduced into the cells. <lb/>After 16 hours of processing the Premo™ reagent, the media was replaced with a medium with or without 1.6mg/ <lb/>ml PPMPs, and consecutive images were recorded every 5 minutes for 24 hours in a chamber maintained at <lb/>37 °C with 5% CO 2 . <lb/>Statistical analysis. Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism Version 9 (GraphPad, Inc., <lb/>USA). All data were reported as the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM), and p-values were determined <lb/>using an unpaired t test or one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Significant differences between the groups <lb/>were established at the following p-values: * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.001, and **** p &lt; 0.0001. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports | <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Results <lb/>Characterization of polypropylene microplastics (PPMPs). The SEM images were used to confirm <lb/>the morphology of the PPMP fragment types, and a variety of shapes were observed (Fig. 1A). The most frequent <lb/>size of the PPMP fragments was around 16.4 µm (Fig. 1B). We did not separate out the larger-sized PPMPs <lb/>(more than 20 µm) because MPs produced in the real world exist in various sizes and shapes, and humans do <lb/>not use different pathways to uptake the different sized and shaped PPMPs but indiscriminately uptake PPMPs <lb/>smaller than 200 µm in size. Therefore, we focused on studying MPs similar to what exists in the real world. <lb/>Generally, plastic products contain artificial synthetic chemicals, such as processing aids, plasticizers, rein-<lb/>forcing agents, light stabilizers, oxidizing agents, flame retardants, and foaming agents. Therefore, we examined <lb/>the contribution of the chemicals leaked from the MPs used in this study. To evaluate these chemicals, we added <lb/>fragmented MPs to the complete medium and incubated them for 72 hours. We then detected the extracted <lb/>chemicals from the MPs using HPLC/DAD. There was no significant difference between the extracted chemicals <lb/>from the vehicle and MPs (Fig. 1C). These results suggest that chemicals were not extracted from the MPs during <lb/>the incubation. Therefore, all the physiological observations in this study were effects of the MPs. <lb/>PPMPs did not show cytotoxicity. In order to assess the cytotoxicity of the MPs, PPMPs were added <lb/>to MDA-MB-231 cells at various concentrations (0, 0.4, 0.8, 1.2, 1.6, and 2 mg/ml). The cell viability was meas-<lb/>Figure 1. Characterization and SEM images of the PPMPs (A) SEM images of the fragment type PPMPs (B) <lb/>The particle size distribution plot of the PPMPs indicates that the PP particles have the largest volume density <lb/>(%) at 16.40 μm. (C) Comparison of the HPLC chromatograms before (left, Vehicle) and after the microplastic <lb/>treatment at the selective adsorptions (right, PPMP). <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>ured 24 hours after the administration of the PPMPs. The cell viability was not affected by the PPMP treat-<lb/>ment regardless of their concentration, suggesting that the PPMPs did not induce cytotoxicity in these breast <lb/>cancer cells (Fig. 2A). For subsequent experiments in this study, we wanted to apply the highest concentration <lb/>of PPMPs that did not affect the viability of the MDA-MB-231 cells. Although the PPMP-induced toxicity was <lb/>not statistically significant, the cell viability was slightly decreased at 2.0 mg/ml (94.5%) compared with 1.6 mg/ <lb/>ml (102.4%), so all subsequent experiments were performed using 1.6 mg/ml PPMPs. After adding 1.6 mg/ml <lb/>PPMPs for 24 hours, the cells were fixed and subjected to SEM imaging. PPMPs were sitting down to the surface <lb/>of cells or inserted between cells (Fig. 2B). Altered cellular shape and morphology were not observed in the <lb/>ultrastructural analysis. Since most of the PPMPs tended to float in the medium when treated, small portion of <lb/>PPMPs were sunken to the cellular membrane or the bottom of the plate (Fig. 2B). <lb/>PPMPs did not alter cellular motility in breast cancer cells. Cancer metastasis is associated with cel-<lb/>lular migration and motility. To investigate whether the PPMP exposure affected the migration of human breast <lb/>cancer cells, PPMPs were administered to hormone-dependent MCF-7 (ER+, PR+, HER2-) and hormone-inde-<lb/>pendent triple-negative MDA-MB-231 (ER-, PR-, HER2-) cells. The cell motility was observed by time-lapse <lb/>imaging over six hours. The plot shows the path and location of the cell movement by the line from the center <lb/>(0, 0) (Fig. 3). The rates of 360 cells in each group were quantified and displayed in the graph. As a result, the <lb/>exposure to PPMPs in the MDA-MB-231 cells did not affect the direction and speed of the cancer cell motility. <lb/>These results were consistent in both the MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 cells (Fig. 3A,B). <lb/>Further, the wound-healing ability of both breast cancer cell types, MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7, was exam-<lb/>ined. The cell migration analysis was performed after exposing the cells to 1.6 mg/ml PPMPs for 12 hours. <lb/>Similarly, the presence of PPMPs did not alter the tendency of wound closure in the MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 <lb/>cells (Fig. 3C,D). These results suggest that PPMP exposure does not affect cancer cell motility regardless of the <lb/>properties of the breast cancer cells. <lb/>PPMPs induced transcriptional changes in RNA-seq analysis. An RNA-seq was performed on the <lb/>MDA-MB-231 cells with or without PPMP incubation to investigate whether the 1.6mg/ml PPMPs affected gene <lb/>expression related to breast cancer progression. After the read alignment and quantification, the initial evaluation <lb/>of the dataset was performed. Using 18,000 of the most expressed transcripts and a principal component analysis <lb/>(PCA) plot, we assessed the differences among the samples collected from cells with or without PPMPs (Fig. 4A). <lb/>The first and second principal components accounted for the largest variance among the datasets generated from <lb/>the RNA-Seq dataset. The application of EdgeR with conservative access to the RNA-seq data gained from the <lb/>PPMP-treated samples confirmed that there were 1717 differentially expressed transcripts (Fig. 4B). The volcano <lb/>plots show the statistical significance of the differentially expressed transcripts (DETs) with the respective fold-<lb/>changes (p &lt; 0.01, absolute log2 fold-change [log2 FC] &gt; 1) compared with the control group. The significant <lb/>upregulation (753 transcripts) or downregulation (964 transcripts) of genes was revealed in the PPMP-treated <lb/>breast cancer cells (Fig. 4B). Hierarchical clustering of the upregulated (343) or downregulated (319) DETs <lb/>in the PPMP-treated cells were classified into two categories with stringent filtering conditions (p &lt; 0.01, log2 <lb/>FC &gt; 1.5) (Fig. 4C). The top enriched gene ontology (GO) cellular components and biological processes of the <lb/>PPMP-exposed cells were visualized from the significant DETs of the upregulated genes as cluster 1 of Fig. 4C. <lb/>Following the GO enrichment analysis, the cell cycle, cell-matrix adhesion, adenylate cyclase activity, and fatty <lb/>acid metabolic processes were revealed to be the most significantly enriched pathways in the PPMP-treated cells <lb/>(Fig. 4D). Among them, G1/S phase transition-related transcript levels were the most highly impacted by the <lb/>PPMP exposure. Thus, we evaluated the expression of cell cycle-related genes by qRT-PCR. The selected genes <lb/>Figure 2. Effect of PPMP on cell viability in human breast cancer cells. (A) PPMPs were added to the <lb/>MDA-MB-231 cells and incubated for 24 hours. The graph shows the survival rates of cells with or without <lb/>PPMPs (n = 3 independent experiments; one-way ANOVA, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 relative to 0 mg/ml PPMPs). <lb/>(B) SEM image shows MDA-MB-231 cells with or without PPMPs for 24 hours. The red arrows indicate a <lb/>PPMP on the cell surface. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 3. Effect of PPMP on breast cancer cell motility. (A) Both breast cancer cell lines were incubated with <lb/>PPMPs and observed under a time-lapse imaging microscope for six hours. The plots depict the motility of <lb/>individual cells in the representative experiment. (B) Quantification of the migration speed reveals unchanged <lb/>cellular velocity by the PPMPs treatment in both cell lines. The results are expression as the mean ± SEM; n <lb/>= 360 individual cells for both cell lines. (unpaired two-tailed t test, p = 0.7629 for the MDA-MB-231 cells <lb/>and p = 0.1116 for the MCF-7 cells). (C) and (D) Effects of the PPMPs on the ability of wound healing in <lb/>the MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 cell lines. Photos in each group were taken at 0 hours and 12 hours after the <lb/>PPMP treatment. The closed area (indicated yellow line) was quantified by Image J software. Experiments were <lb/>repeated independently three times for the MCF-7 cells and five times for the MDA-MB-231 cells (unpaired <lb/>two-tailed t test; p = 0.0684 for the MDA-MB-231 cells, p = 0.7760 for the MCF-7 cells). <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4. Transcriptomic dynamics in PPMP-treated MDA-MB-231 cells. The common gene expression <lb/>patterns through two independent experiments were identified by transcriptomic analysis using the RNA-seq <lb/>platform. (A) Principal component analysis (PCA) of the RNA-seq analysis. The values indicate the amount of <lb/>variation attributed to each principal component. The small circles indicate individual samples, blue asterisks <lb/>indicate the average between experimental replicates, and larger gray ovals represent each experimental group. <lb/>(B) The volcano plot from the filtered significant DETs from the MDA-MB-231 cells with or without the PPMP <lb/>incubation. (C) The differential gene expression patterns of DETs in the RNA-seq analysis. The hierarchical <lb/>clustering of genes (rows) and experimental samples (columns) from the RNA-seq data. (D) The top enriched <lb/>GO cellular components and biological processes of PPMP-treated cells, visualized from the significantly <lb/>upregulated DETs from the RNA-seq platform. The size of the circle represents the enriched genes, and the color <lb/>represents -log 10 of the p-value. (E) Transcript levels of TMBIM6, AP2M1, PTP4A2, and FTH1 were evaluated <lb/>by qRT-PCR in MDA-MB-231 cells (unpaired two-tailed t test, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001 relative to the <lb/>vehicle group). <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>were analyzed from cells exposed to PPMPs for 24 hours. The expression of transmembrane BAX inhibitor motif <lb/>containing 6 (TMBIM6) was about 1.52-fold higher in cells treated with PPMPs than in the vehicle-treated cells <lb/>(Fig. 4E). The expression of adaptor related protein complex 2 subunit mu 1 (AP2M1) was increased by about <lb/>1.92-fold in cells treated with PPMPs. Also, the transcript level of protein tyrosine phosphatase 4A2 (PTP4A2) <lb/>was increased by about 1.46-fold in the PPMP-treated cells compared with the vehicle-treated cells. However, <lb/>the expression of the ferritin heavy chain 1 (FTH1) was reduced by about 0.6-fold. These results show that the <lb/>expression of genes related to the cell cycle was affected by the PPMPs. Interestingly, these changes of gene <lb/>expression by PPMP were not observed in normal breast epithelial cells, MCF10A. PPMP incubation could only <lb/>affect breast cancer cells, not normal breast cell line (Supplementary Fig. 1). <lb/>Further, the cell cycle changes in breast cancer cells after exposure to PPMPs were monitored using FUCCI, <lb/>a cell cycle sensor, for 24 hours. Compared with the vehicle, the color change was accelerated by the PPMPs <lb/>from red, indicating G1 phase, to yellow, indicating early S phase (Fig. 5A). In Fig. 5B, the cell cycle phases are <lb/>expressed as percentages at six-hour intervals. After six hours of PPMP treatment, the proportion of cells in the <lb/>S/G2/M phase was increased, suggesting that PPMPs promote cell cycle changes in breast cancer. <lb/>PPMPs increased the secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-6 from cancer cells. Cytokines <lb/>are important mediators in the tumor microenvironment and can function as growth factors to increase cell <lb/>metastasis by promoting extracellular matrix degradation and angiogenesis. In particular, IL-6 is a well-known <lb/>pro-inflammatory cytokine associated with the tumor microenvironment and has been reported to promote cell <lb/>cycle progression, proliferation, anti-apoptosis, and metastasis in breast cancer 15-17 . Since the PPMPs promoted <lb/>the cell cycle of breast cancer cells, we evaluated whether the secretion of IL-6 was increased in cancer cells <lb/>exposed to 1.6mg/ml PPMPs. After exposure to the PPMPs for 24 hours, the secretion of IL-6 was 34.62 ± 1.41 <lb/>ng/ml, which was significantly increased compared with the vehicle in MDA-MB-231 cells (n = 3, 10.60 ± 3.38 <lb/>ng/ml). Similarly, the secretion of IL-6 in the MCF-7 cells was also markedly increased in the PPMP group (5.36 <lb/>± 0.23 pg/ml) compared with the vehicle group (3.98 ± 0.13 pg/ml) (Fig. 6A,B). <lb/>Figure 5. Effect of PPMP on cell cycle in breast cancer cells. (A) FUCCI images were captured after the <lb/>PPMP application at 0, 6, 12 and 24 hours while monitoring the cell cycle of living cells in real-time. The <lb/>scale bar represents 10 µm. (B) Histograms show the cell cycle rate at each time. Cells at each cycle stage were <lb/>quantitatively evaluated by counting the number of cells of each color. Cell cycle profiles are color coded: G1, <lb/>red; initial S, yellow; and late S/G2/M, green (n = 52-129 per group total number of cells). <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>MPs are rapidly emerging as a global challenge that raises concerns about human health and the whole ecosys-<lb/>tem. In addition, the increased use of single-use plastics during the COVID-19 pandemic accelerated an already <lb/>out-of-control global plastic waste problem. <lb/>Most of the research on MPs is confined to the effect of the sphere type MPs; however, most of the MPs in the <lb/>environment are the fragment and fiber type MPs. Therefore, the results of studies on the sphere type MPs are <lb/>prone to provide biased information on the MP risk assessment to human health. To date, studies on the effect of <lb/>shape-dependent MPs are very limited. In this study, we focused on the pathophysiological effect of fragmented <lb/>MPs on cancer cell lines. The PPMPs used in this study were a mixture of fragmented PPMPs of various sizes, <lb/>but the majority had a diameter of 16.4 µm. We demonstrated that the fragmented PPMPs promoted the cell <lb/>cycle, proliferation, and secretion of the inflammatory cytokine IL-6 in human breast cancer cells, while PPMPs <lb/>did not induce cytotoxicity nor enhance cellular motility. <lb/>Various sized MPs can affect cells differently in vitro or in vivo. MPs are reported to have a wide range of sizes <lb/>in freshwater and marine environments, varying from 10 µm to 5 mm 18,19 . The tiniest MPs are called nanoplastics <lb/>and are smaller than 0.1 µm. The accumulation of plastic particles, between the sizes of 5 and 110 µm, in animals, <lb/>such as rats, dogs, and pigs, was reported as early as 1970 20 . Recently, several studies have reported how plastics <lb/>might be harmful in vitro and in vivo and that the size of the MPs determines their uptake efficiency through <lb/>the gastrointestinal, alveolar, and dermal epithelium 21-23 . Although more than 90% of the MPs were reported <lb/>to be excreted in feces, especially larger particles (&gt; 150 µm), smaller MPs may be absorbed systematically. It <lb/>has been reported that MPs 0.1-10 µm in size can cross the blood-brain barrier 24 and the placenta 25 , particles <lb/>smaller than 150 µm can cross the gastrointestinal epithelium, and MPs smaller than 2.5 µm can enter the sys-<lb/>temic circulation system through endocytosis 26 . Thus, the PPMPs in this study were small enough to cross the <lb/>gastrointestinal tract and travel through the body. <lb/>In this study, we applied PPMPs. Polypropylene particles are thought to be harmless polymers according to <lb/>the guidelines from the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) 27 ; however, some studies show that their toxicity is <lb/>mainly due to heat 28 and size 29 . In this study, only a few portion of PPMPs among the 1.6 mg/ml of PPMPs were <lb/>sitting down to the cell surface or bottom of the culture plate (Fig. 2), while most of the PPMPs were floating in <lb/>the medium. Moreover, our ultrastructural analysis showed that most of the PPMPs could not enter the cells. <lb/>Interestingly, the PPMPs sunken between the cell membrane or bottom of the plate did not interrupt the cellular <lb/>migration or motility of cancer cells (Fig. 3). Instead, the PPMPs enhanced IL-6 secretion and the cell cycle of <lb/>breast cancer cells. Based on the GO of the DEGs from the RNA-seq analysis in our study, G1/S phase transition <lb/>and cell-matrix adhesion related pathways were activated (Fig. 4D and Supplementary Fig. 2). We also found <lb/>that the gene expression of TMBIM6, AP2M1, and PTP4A2, which are correlated with cancer progression and <lb/>the cell cycle 30-32 , was significantly increased by PPMP incubation in MDA-MB-231 human breast cancer cells, <lb/>suggesting that PPMPs regulate the transcriptional activity of cancer cells. <lb/>Interestingly, chemical factors could not be detected in our system, although most of the PPMPs were floating <lb/>in the culture medium (Fig. 1C). In general, the chemical compounds from MPs, which are used in most plastic <lb/>processing, are also important factors to be considered. Manufacturers add compounds such as plasticizers, <lb/>stabilizers, and pigments to plastics and many of these substances are hazardous; for example, they can interfere <lb/>with the endocrine system 33 . There are also studies showing that benzophenone-A, a plastic stabilizer, stimulates <lb/>the proliferation of ovarian cancer and breast cancer 34 , and several other chemicals have been shown to have <lb/>various effects on cell cycle, proliferation, and the reproductive system 35,36 . <lb/>Based on the results in Fig. 1C, we concluded that the physical effect of PPMPs on the breast cell line drives <lb/>cancer progression rather than the chemical effect. PPMPs attached to the cell membrane or inserted between <lb/>cells may alter the physical contact or stimuli in human breast cancer cells, followed by the enhancement of <lb/>cancer progressions, such as the cell cycle and IL-6 secretion. However, the chemical effect of PPMPs cannot <lb/>be excluded. Since the cell culture medium is generally composed of a complement of amino acids, vitamins, <lb/>Figure 6. Effect of PPMP on pro-inflammatory cytokines in breast cancer cells. (A) and (B) IL-6 secretion was <lb/>evaluated by an ELISA in MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 breast cancer cells (unpaired two-tailed t test, ***p &lt; 0.001, <lb/>n = 3 for the MDA-MB-231 cells; n = 6 for the MCF-7 cells). <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			Vol:.(1234567890) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>inorganic salts, glucose, and serum, which are large-sized biological molecules, there might have been techni-<lb/>cal limitations in the detection of small-sized chemicals. The exact mechanisms of MPs should be investigated <lb/>further. Overall, our results demonstrate that PPMPs can promote tumor progression by promoting the inflam-<lb/>matory cytokine IL-6 secretion and cell cycle progression in breast cancer cells. These data support new evidence <lb/>of the potential risks of MPs. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In this study, we observed that PPMPs with irregular shapes affected human breast cancer cells; notably, expo-<lb/>sure to PPMPs increased cell cycle-related gene expression and IL-6 secretion from MDA-MB-231 and MCF7 <lb/>cells. Moreover, 1.6 mg/ml of PPMPs used in this study might be a high concentration for cancer cells, but this <lb/>concentration neither induced cell death nor altered the migration ability of breast cancer cells. Additionally, the <lb/>RNA-seq analysis revealed that PPMPs promoted metastatic features in cancer cells instead. <lb/>Although many researchers have reported the detrimental effects of MPs on our health, a comprehensive <lb/>analysis of the chemical and physical effects of MPs has yet to be conducted. Here, we demonstrated for the first <lb/>time the effect MPs have on human breast cancer. During and after the COVID-19 pandemic, the indiscriminate <lb/>use of plastics may exacerbate the harmful effects of MPs on our health. Therefore, this study is a starting point <lb/>for the discussion between the chronic exposure to MPs and cancer progression. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>All data analyzed during this study are included in this published article and its supplementary information file. <lb/>The datasets used in Fig. 4 and supplementary information are downloaded from Gene Expression Omnibus <lb/>(GEO) database under accession number GSE219207. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 27 November 2022; Accepted: 12 April 2023 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Hartmann, N. B. et al. Are we speaking the same language? Recommendations for a definition and categorization framework for <lb/>plastic debris. Environ. Sci. Technol. 53, 1039-1047 (2019). <lb/>2. Machado, A. A. D., Kloas, W., Zarfl, C., Hempel, S. &amp; Rillig, M. C. Microplastics as an emerging threat to terrestrial ecosystems. <lb/>Glob. Change Biol. 24, 1405-1416 (2018). <lb/>3. Prata, J. C. Airborne microplastics: Consequences to human health?. Environ. Pollut. 234, 115-126 (2018). <lb/>4. Barboza, L. G. A., Vethaak, A. D., Lavorante, B., Lundebye, A. K. &amp; Guilhermino, L. Marine microplastic debris: An emerging issue <lb/>for food security, food safety and human health. Mar. Pollut. Bull. 133, 336-348 (2018). <lb/>5. Kosuth, M., Mason, S. A. &amp; Wattenberg, E. V. Anthropogenic contamination of tap water, beer, and sea salt. PLoS One 13, e0194970 <lb/>(2018). <lb/>6. Schymanski, D., Goldbeck, C., Humpf, H. U. &amp; Furst, P. Analysis of microplastics in water by micro-Raman spectroscopy: Release <lb/>of plastic particles from different packaging into mineral water. Water Res. 129, 154-162 (2018). <lb/>7. Deng, Y., Zheng, Y., Lemos, B. &amp; Ren, H. Tissue accumulation of microplastics in mice and biomarker responses suggest widespread <lb/>health risks of exposure. Sci. Rep. 7, 46687 (2017). <lb/>8. Schwabl, P. et al. Detection of various microplastics in human stool a prospective case series. Ann. Intern. Med. 171, 453-457 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>9. Rahman, A., Sarkar, A., Yadav, O. P., Achari, G. &amp; Slobodnik, J. Potential human health risks due to environmental exposure to <lb/>nano-and microplastics and knowledge gaps: A scoping review. Sci. Total Environ. 757, 143872 (2021). <lb/>10. Campanale, C., Massarelli, C., Savino, I., Locaputo, V. &amp; Uricchio, V. F. Detailed review study on potential effects of microplastics <lb/>and additives of concern on human health. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 17, 1212 (2020). <lb/>11. Kannan, K. &amp; Vimalkumar, K. A review of human exposure to microplastics and insights into microplastics as obesogens. Front. <lb/>Endocrinol. 12, 724989 (2021). <lb/>12. Peng, Y., Wu, P., Schartup, A. T. &amp; Zhang, Y. Plastic waste release caused by COVID-19 and its fate in the global ocean. Proc. Natl. <lb/>Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 118, e2111530118 (2021). <lb/>13. Yang, C. Z., Yaniger, S. I., Jordan, V. C., Klein, D. J. &amp; Bittner, G. D. Most plastic products release estrogenic chemicals: A potential <lb/>health problem that can be solved. Environ. Health Perspect. 119, 989-996 (2011). <lb/>14. Rodgers, K. M., Udesky, J. O., Rudel, R. A. &amp; Brody, J. G. Environmental chemicals and breast cancer: An updated review of epi-<lb/>demiological literature informed by biological mechanisms. Environ. Res. 160, 158-182 (2018). <lb/>15. Barbieri, I. et al. Constitutively active Stat3 enhances neu-mediated migration and metastasis in mammary tumors via upregulation <lb/>of Cten. Cancer Res. 70, 2558-2567 (2010). <lb/>16. Carpenter, R. L. &amp; Lo, H. W. STAT3 target genes relevant to human cancers. Cancers 6, 897-925 (2014). <lb/>17. Yu, H., Kortylewski, M. &amp; Pardoll, D. Crosstalk between cancer and immune cells: Role of STAT3 in the tumour microenviron-<lb/>ment. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 7, 41-51 (2007). <lb/>18. Bergmann, M. et al. High quantities of microplastic in arctic deep-sea sediments from the HAUSGARTEN observatory. Environ. <lb/>Sci. Technol. 51, 11000-11010 (2017). <lb/>19. Reisser, J. et al. The vertical distribution of buoyant plastics at sea: An observational study in the North Atlantic Gyre. Biogeosciences <lb/>12, 1249-1256 (2015). <lb/>20. Volkheimer, G. Hematogenous dissemination of ingested polyvinyl chloride particles. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 246, 164-171 (1975). <lb/>21. Banerjee, A. &amp; Shelver, W. L. Micro-and nanoplastic induced cellular toxicity in mammals: A review. Sci. Total Environ. 755, 142518 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>22. Luo, T. et al. Maternal exposure to different sizes of polystyrene microplastics during gestation causes metabolic disorders in their <lb/>offspring. Environ. Pollut. 255, 113122 (2019). <lb/>23. Walczak, A. P. et al. Translocation of differently sized and charged polystyrene nanoparticles in in vitro intestinal cell models of <lb/>increasing complexity. Nanotoxicology 9, 453-461 (2015). <lb/>24. Prüst, M., Meijer, J. &amp; Westerink, R. H. S. The plastic brain: Neurotoxicity of micro-and nanoplastics. Part. Fibre Toxicol. 17, 24 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>25. Chain, F. Presence of microplastics and nanoplastics in food, with particular focus on seafood. EFSA J. 14, e04501 (2016). <lb/>26. Campanale, C., Massarelli, C., Savino, I., Locaputo, V. &amp; Uricchio, V. F. A detailed review study on potential effects of microplastics <lb/>and additives of concern on human health. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 17, 1212 (2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			Vol.:(0123456789) <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Reports <lb/>| <lb/>(2023) 13:6252 | <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-33393-8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>27. Clayman, H. M. Polypropylene. Ophthalmology 88, 959-964 (1981). <lb/>28. Song, Y., Begley, T., Paquette, K. &amp; Komolprasert, V. Effectiveness of polypropylene film as a barrier to migration from recycled <lb/>paperboard packaging to fatty and high-moisture food. Food Addit. Contam. 20, 875-883 (2003). <lb/>29. Hwang, J., Choi, D., Han, S., Choi, J. &amp; Hong, J. An assessment of the toxicity of polypropylene microplastics in human derived <lb/>cells. Sci. Total Environ. 684, 657-669 (2019). <lb/>30. Duff, M. D. et al. Regulation of senescence escape by the cdk4-EZH2-AP2M1 pathway in response to chemotherapy. Cell Death <lb/>Dis. 9, 199 (2018). <lb/>31. Gao, Y. et al. Over-expression of protein tyrosine phosphatase 4A2 correlates with tumor progression and poor prognosis in <lb/>nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Oncotarget 8, 77527-77539 (2017). <lb/>32. Kim, H. K. et al. TMBIM6/BI-1 contributes to cancer progression through assembly with mTORC2 and AKT activation. Nat. <lb/>Commun. 11, 4012 (2020). <lb/>33. Lim, X. Z. Microplastics are everywhere-But are they harmful?. Nature 593, 22-25 (2021). <lb/>34. Dumitrascu, M. C. et al. Carcinogenic effects of bisphenol A in breast and ovarian cancers. Oncol. Lett. 20, 282 (2020). <lb/>35. Eales, J. et al. Human health impacts of exposure to phthalate plasticizers: An overview of reviews. Environ. Int. 158, 106903 (2022). <lb/>36. Meeker, J. D., Sathyanarayana, S. &amp; Swan, S. H. Phthalates and other additives in plastics: Human exposure and associated health <lb/>outcomes. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci. 364, 2097-2113 (2009). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>J.H.P., S.H., O.-H.K., C.-H.K. and J.K. contributed to methodology, validation, analysis and writing. J.-W.K., <lb/>S.H. and H.J.L. contributed to conceptualization, data curation, visualization and writing-original draft, editing <lb/>and funding acquisition. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This work was supported by a National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korean gov-<lb/>ernment (Grant No. 2020R1A2C2011617) and the Korea Environment Industry &amp; Technology Institute (KEITI) <lb/>through the Measurement and Risk assessment Program for Management of Microplastics Program, funded <lb/>by the Korea Ministry of Environment (MOE) (2021003120002). The Korea Environment Industry &amp; Technol-<lb/>ogy Institute through &quot;Digital Infrastructure Building Project for Monitoring, Surveying and Evaluating the <lb/>Environmental Health Program (No. 2021003330007)&quot; funded by the Korea Ministry of Environment (MOE). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Additional information <lb/>Supplementary Information The online version contains supplementary material available at https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1038/ s41598-023-33393-8. <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to J.-W.K., S.H. or H.J.L. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the <lb/>Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from <lb/>the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http:// creat iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2023 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
